<html xmlns:v="urn:schemas-microsoft-com:vml" xmlns:o="urn:schemas-microsoft-com:office:office" xmlns:w="urn:schemas-microsoft-com:office:word" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-html40"><head><title>Abstracts</title><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=windows-1252" /><meta name="ProgId" content="Word.Document" /><meta name="Generator" content="Microsoft Word 11" /><meta name="Originator" content="Microsoft Word 11" /><xml><o:DocumentProperties><o:Author>Oxford Abstracts Ltd</o:Author><o:LastAuthor>Kim Wilson</o:LastAuthor><o:Company>Oxford Abstracts Ltd</o:Company></o:DocumentProperties><w:WordDocument><w:View>Print</w:View><w:GrammarState>Clean</w:GrammarState><w:ValidateAgainstSchemas /><w:SaveIfXMLInvalid>false</w:SaveIfXMLInvalid><w:IgnoreMixedContent>false</w:IgnoreMixedContent><w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText>false</w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText><w:Compatibility><w:SelectEntireFieldWithStartOrEnd /><w:UseWord2002TableStyleRules /></w:Compatibility><w:BrowserLevel>MicrosoftInternetExplorer4</w:BrowserLevel></w:WordDocument></xml><style>
          BODY, TD, Table, p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal {
          mso-style-parent:"";
          margin:0cm;
          margin-bottom:0pt;
          margin-top:10pt;
          mso-pagination:widow-orphan;
          font-size:10.0pt;
          font-family:"Arial";
          mso-fareast-font-family:"Times New Roman";
          mso-ansi-language:EN-GB;
          mso-fareast-language:EN-US;}
        </style></head><body><o:wrapblock /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0002</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>The Effects of the Mentoring System on the Achievement of student in Project Management Course</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Education al Research Methods</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Tomas Ganiron Jr</u><sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Qassim University, Buraidah City, Saudi Arabia,<sup> 2</sup>AUT, Auckland, New Zealand,<sup> 3</sup>FEATI University, Manila, The Philippines</em></p><p>The quasi-experimental design involving two groups of 105 engineering student in Project Management course of comparable mental ability was used in this study. One group was exposed to mentoring system while the other was not. Test result in practical problem solving case studies and achievement test of two equivalent classes in Project Management were compared for 3 grading periods. The experimental class (n=50) was taught using the mentoring system strategy while control (n=55) was taught the traditional method, which is predominantly teacher-oriented. It was found that the mentoring system strategy improved the student practical problem solving case studies ability only slightly increased achievement test scores, it made the engineering student more responsible to each other. This was visible when the mentoring tutor prepared his own exercises for the tutorial sessions; the engineering student who were taught in mentoring system strategy gave detailed SWOT analysis in case study of project management course.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0003</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Enhancing the Civil Engineering Project Courses in the BSCE Curriculum of FEATI University</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Tomas Ganiron Jr</u> <em>FEATI University, Manila, The Philippines</em></p><p>Several momentous and significant events happening all over the world make the paradigm change in the method of teaching in the Philippines. The first is globalization. High technology has shrunk the world so drastically that professionals have to compete with others in their field internationally. This simply means that if Civil Engineering student will not learn to research and invent new technology, the newly CE graduates will hardly stand a chance in the global competition. The design of Civil Engineering Project courses that will use their technical engineering knowledge in construction and management engineering, highway and transportation engineering, structural engineering and water resources engineering will enhance or prove concepts will go a long way in developing future civil engineers who are aware, concerned and innovative in dealing with work situations. This research paper presents innovations made in the project courses of the Civil Engineering program in line with the objective of enhancing the learning process. Civil engineers become more effective if he has acquired the proper education and training.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0004</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Adapting Team-Based Learning to FacilitateDevelopment of Competencies and Skills Needed for Global Engineering Competitiveness</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Global Engineer</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Robert O'Connell</u> <em>University of Missouri, Columbia, Missouri, USA</em></p><p>Industry and accrediting agencies are telling us that when many of today's engineering student enter the work force, they will find themselves on multi-disciplinary and diverse international teams solving global-scale problems. The skills needed to be successful in that setting include superior technical competence and excellent professional skills. Research shows that student-centred active learning tends to produce better conceptual understanding than does traditional passive lecture-based learning, and that when active learning is conducted in an extensively group-based environment, student can also develop various professional skills, such as self-directed independent learning, problem-solving,and interpersonal team skills. Team-Based Learning (TBL) is a form of group-based student-centred learning in which student independently study new conceptual material before it is treated in the classroom, and then subsequently spend considerable classroom time working in teams on increasingly challenging applications of that new material. A recent initiative to use TBL as the principal teaching and learning strategy in the second-year electric circuit theory sequence has led to several beneficial revisions to the basic TBL process. This paper describes those changes, with emphasis on professional skills development. Continuous assessment instruments used to assess learning of professional skills are described, and evaluative measures that illustrate the effectiveness of the revised strategy are also described.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0006</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Curriculum Development of Hardware Interfacing System for Visual C++ in Computer Engineering Course</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Doyce Tesoro-Martinez</u><sup>1</sup>, Harold Taylor<sup>1</sup>, Tomas Ganiron Jr<sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>University of Auckland, Auckland, New Zealand,<sup> 2</sup>Victoria University of Wellington, Wellington, New Zealand,<sup> 3</sup>Auckland University of Technology, Auckland, New Zealand</em></p><p>The College of Computer Engineering rides stop the crest of the new millennium. This is the reason of its curriculum revision in hardware interfacing system course. Furthermore, the revision was made for the course to be internationally and globally competitive, relevant to local conditions and with strong industry linkage components. Although this course was comparable to that of most other university, it had neither the rigour nor the practical experience needed to prepare undergraduates for the workplace or meaningful graduate study. The student and faculty responses have been very favourable. They are excited by the new course and the closed laboratory component. The hardware interfacing system course has lecture slides, laboratory activities, homework assignments, etc. available on the web for public viewing</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0007</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Virtuality, interdisciplinarity, collaborativeness: Assessing student outcomes for I-EDU Innovative Engineering Instructional Project</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Hsiou-huai Wang</u> <em>National Taiwan University, Taipei, Taiwan</em></p><p>The rapid development of information technology propels knowledge explosion and the progress of human civilization. Meanwhile, the ubiquitous computers, internet, and mobile devices have changed the means people absorb and create knowledge. Recently, cultivating creativity as an ability and building creative talent has become the focus for the higher education researchers in the engineering and design realm.</p><p>Consequently, the current research centers on establishing and evaluating an innovative engineering instructional model (I-EDU Project) , which aims to ameliorate student' passive and conventional individual-focused learning model, as well as to enhance their essential competencies such as exploration, reflection, teamwork and creativity. I-EDU project consists of six projects, with five innovative course projects and an assessment study, implemented in a comprehensive university in Taiwan. I-EDU proposes three major instructional elements, that is, virtuality, interdisciplinary and collaborativeness, implemented in the five innovative engineering courses to increase student' core competencies, including: observation, reflection, imagination, teamwork and interdisciplinary communication.</p><p>The current research is I-EDU's assessment project, taking the role of evaluating and examining student outcomes of the five innovative engineering courses. Specifically, this research examines how the design of these courses characteristic of virtuality, interdisciplinarity and collaborativeness made impact on student' imagination and creativity. Through literature review, expert consultation, establishment of questionnaires, and instructional experiment, this research assessed student outcomes in order to provide timely feedback for the project courses. Ultimately, the result of this current research are beneficial to setting indicative reference for cultivating innovative engineering talent and increase their competitiveness.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0008</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Sustainable development in Engineering university, how accreditation agencies can help them in this demarch? The case of French HEIandits application in Polytech Orl?s</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Sustainability in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Anne-Marie JOLLY</u><sup>1
                    ,2</sup>, Christophe LEGER<sup>1</sup>, Jean-Yves CADOREL<sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Universit?'Orl?s, Orl?s, France,<sup> 2</sup>Commission des Titres d' Ing?eurs, France, France</em></p><p>Though much work has been done since 2002 at the European level to include Sustainable Development in Engineering Education, it appears that a rather important part of Engineering HEIs has not included SD in its global strategy.  After an incitation period, it is perhaps necessary to go to mandatory actions. Quality agencies can be the frame for such actions. As an example, in February 2014, the French Agency "Commission des Titres d' Ing?eurs" made mandatory for all engineering education institutions to define a strategy concerning sustainable development and to apply it. It became immediately a criteria for evaluation. As in the ISO norms concerning SD, many fields are concerned:the strategy and policy of the institution, the social management and link with the territory, the environmental management, research, education, documentation, links with enterprises, the quality and progress strategy of the institution. Each institution can implement Green Plan according to its specificities. As an example of application, the way Polytech Orl?s has implemented these recommendations to its specificity, implying student, teachers and stake holders is presented together with others examples of "Green Plan" in Engineering institutions.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0009</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Perspectives and Expectations of Engineering Curriculum and Graduates' Employability by StakeholdersBased on the Survey to 6 university and 20 Enterprises in China</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Jun Cui</u>, Jian Chen <em>Southeast University, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China</em></p><p>  The purpose of this paper is to illustrate the perspectives and expectations from engineering education stakeholders including graduates and employers for engineering curriculum and graduates' employability.</p><p>  This study contains three research questions. First, how satisfied are senior student with the curricula enhancing employability? Second, how satisfied and expected are employers with the employability of engineering graduates? Third, what're the differences among graduates' satisfaction, employers' satisfaction and employers' expectation?</p><p>  Questionnaire investigations and interviews are combined to collect data and both stratified sampling and purposive sampling method are adopted. Student samples are 600 senior student from 6 university and employer samples are 300 employers from 20 enterprises. The location regions, engineering fields and types of the enterprises are evenly distributed.</p><p>  The result of this study are as followings. First, student' satisfaction degree of the curricula enhancing employability is not high, which is significantly different in university and fields. Second, employers' satisfaction degree of engineering graduates' employability is not high either and there is a gap between employers' satisfaction and their expectation. Third, student' satisfaction degree of the curricula enhancing employability and employers' satisfaction degree of graduates' employability are significantly lower than employers' expectation value.</p><p>  The author conclude that engineering curriculum reform must take the stakeholders' demand into account integrate employability into curricula and focus on developing student technical hard skills as well as non-technical soft skills. This study provides empirical evidence from perspectives of stakeholders for cultivating engineers of high quality and deepening the reform of engineering curriculum.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0010</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>activities Led Learning and Developing Professional Judgement Capacity in Undergraduate Learners.</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Hal Igarashi</u>, John Davies, Sarah Wilson-Medhurst <em>Coventry University, Coventry, UK</em></p><p>activities Led Learning and Developing Professional Judgement Capacity in Undergraduate Learners.</p><p>Hal Igarashi, John Davies, Sarah Wilson-Medhurst. Coventry University.</p><p><b>Abstract:</b></p><p>Research has indicated that the domain specific knowledge of new professional entrants and professional experts is largely similar, and that professional performance of experts is predicated in flexible behaviours and the way that professionals organise knowledge and exercise judgement. Traditionally new professional entrants acquired these skills in a community of practice after leaving university. This paper proposes that activities Led Learning (ALL) with strong relevance to the dynamics and structuralism of real world problems, may provide a learning environment in which the learner can organise and analyse information and exercise the making of judgements to synthesize new knowledge and develop modified or new habits of action. An opportunistic sample of undergraduate and apprentice engineering learners participating in a range of self directed engineering projects were observed and their activities and learning environment recorded. The projects ran for durations of between 10 to 32 weeks. A range of learners were selected at random and interviewed. The data collected was encoded to determine the kinds of judgements the learners made. Preliminary findings within the experiences observed suggest that ALL experiences can be constructed to provide opportunities that compel learners to exercise making complex judgements across a diverse range of technical and holistic contexts similar to those of engineering professionals.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0011</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Working with student' diversity toward high-level skills by means of PBL</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Issues of Gender and Diversity</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Nestor Arana-Arexolaleiba</u>, I?? Velez-de-Mendizabal, E?? Muxika-Olasagasti, Txema Perez-Lazare <em>Mondragon University, Arrasate-Mondrag??Spain</em></p><p>Nowadays, university offer its services to a greater diversity of student. During 20th century, university have passed from an elite university, to a mass university with a larger proportion of cohorts. In the mass university there is a greater variety of student with different learning approach. Nevertheless, society is asking for student with high-level skills. Those skills go beyond understanding basic knowledge and acquiring basic skills. It is well known that Problem and Project Based Learning (PBL) methodology is adapted to acquire such skills. In this work, we wish to understand the impact of the student's learning approach and their supervisions sessions on high level skills in a PBL context. To carry out this study, Design Based Research method has been used. Several information sources have been used: At the beginning and at the end of the process student' learning approach has been measured. In addition, two different non structured focus group discussions have been organized: the first one with supervisors and the second one with student. In this paper, preliminary result will be shown and discussed.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0012</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Competence-oriented assignments in the mathematical education of mechanical engineers</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Maths in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Burkhard Alpers</u> <em>Aalen University, Aalen, Germany</em></p><p>In the new edition of the curriculum document issued by SEFI's Mathematics Working Group in 2013 (see http://sefi.htw-aalen.de) the concept of mathematical competence as developed in the Danish KOM project serves to capture higher-level learning goals in the mathematical education of engineers. Mathematical competence is defined as "the ability to understand, judge, do and use mathematics in a variety of intra- and extra-mathematical contexts and situations where mathematics plays or could play a role". Assignments given to student are the most important vehicle for achieving educational goals in mathematics (ranging from small, well-defined computational tasks to open and challenging projects). Therefore, for really putting the competence concept into practice, we need assignments that are suitable for acquiring the competence goals (for example those stated by the author in a mathematics curriculum for a practice-oriented study course in mechanical engineering, cf. the website stated above).</p><p>In this contribution, we present examples for such assignments in the area of mechanical engineering and we state some guidelines on how to identify such tasks. It should be mentioned that this type of assignment does not make the usual computational training tasks obsolete since it is well-recognised in the competence concept that a sound knowledge and skills base is a necessary but not sufficient requirement for a person to be mathematically competent. The examples can also serve further purposes: they can be used to convince colleagues that the pedagogical concept has a real meaning, and they can also be used for competence assessment.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0013</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Description of an e-learning tutorial in geostatistics delivered at one university and at one company</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Technology in Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>R? Crepon</u><sup>1
                    ,2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>University Complutense, Madrid, Spain,<sup> 2</sup>aPi-learning, Caluire, France</em></p><p>In 2011, we started a research study in engineering education aiming to make explicit the assumptions and decisions for the design of digital learning resources that would support learning in both academia and industry. For the purpose of the investigation based on design research methodology, an e-learning tutorial in geostatistics has been designed, in real world settings and in collaboration with instructors from industry and teachers from university. The learning resource has been implemented in parallel with class lectures for blended learning at one company and at one engineering school. The module has been refined iteratively along the process.</p><p>The paper is a description of the e-learning module and of its application in academic and corporate contexts. The e-learning resource is a self-paced tutorial which provides basic knowledge in geostatistics prior to learners' participation to class. It involves 2D illustrations, interactive animations, voice-over, exercises, two quizzes, a tracking system that is SCORM<sup>TM</sup> compliant and other functionalities. Each time, the provision has been adapted to the course constraints of the client institution. In addition, we analyze the concepts in geoscience and their relations (discipline or content knowledge), the way they are usually represented and transmitted to the learners (pedagogical knowledge) and their impact on the design and usage of the e-learning module. To finish, we discuss the choices of technology that have been made to support learning in the particular context of the study (technology affordance).</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0014</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Educating new Global Engineers by re-cycling the old ones</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Global Engineer</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Alan Fitzgerald</u> <em>Aston University, Birmingham, UK</em></p><p></p><p>"Educating new Global Engineers by re-cycling the old ones"</p><p></p><p>Abstract</p><p>This paper is an examination and distillation of 6-years' experience supervising Work-Based Learning MSc Professional Engineering programme for company-based student in the UK, Indonesia, Angola and Azerbaijan. The student are seeking to become registered as UK Chartered Engineers by undertaking this programme, at the same time as holding down demanding jobs. All of the overseas student workfor Oil and Gas companies - one of the world's truly  Global Industries' that need  Global Engineers'.</p><p>The Engineering Council pioneered the  Engineering Gateways' scheme as another route to registration in 2006, with a 3-year pilot programme. In 2010 Aston University decided to offer the programme overseas (as well as the UK) in response to requests from BP. These programme are tailored around each participant's job, and develop a series of Reports for assessment, each addressing a specific themed generic academic module. Professional' Supervision of the MSc is usually carried out by retired or semi-retired Chartered Engineers, who pass on their expertise and experience to today's budding Global Engineers.</p><p>The result so far show some fascinating  cultural' influences that took time to understand. The participants are all, in the main,  mature' individuals who develop unique coping mechanisms to handle job pressures and self-motivation issues. The programme is not for everyone! A rigorous selection process helps us identify those individuals who can cope with this challenging route to CEng registration, through the MSc Professional Engineering approach. These are the Global Engineers of tomorrow.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0015</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Review of Engineering Mathematics curriculum at UCD in light of qualitative changes in secondary-school mathematics education in IrelandNiall J. English, School of Chemical and Bioprocess Engineering, UCD, Belfield, Dublin 4, Ireland</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Maths in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Either</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Niall English</u> <em>UCD, Dublin, Ireland</em></p><p>In view of the recent introduction (circa 2010-2012) of the  Project Mathematics  syllabus for the Irish school-leaving ( Leaving Certificate ) examinations (and subsequent two-year  lag  before this cohort of student reached university in Ireland and elsewhere), it has become necessary to recast, revise and alter the timing of the engineering-mathematics curriculum at University College Dublin. This paper discusses these necessary changes and curriculum redesign to accommodate student who have been taught mathematics at secondary school in Ireland in a qualitatively different way to more traditional, teacher-led approach in which there is a strong hierarchical taxonomy: the main structural  shift  at secondary-school level has been towards a more problem-based learning approach. At UCD, changes have resulted in a time-compression and redesign in mathematical coverage in first year in two modules (each 36 lectures and 12 tutorials) whose current syllabuses were revised especially in terms of calculus, vectors and linear algebra to  mesh  in a more seamless way with the  Project Mathematics  syllabus. In terms of resultant,  knock-on  effects on syllabi in subsequent years, the primary changes were in a second-year course on multi-variable calculus, with the placement of other material, such as vector calculus, Fourier analysis and applications to physical problems, placed in a third-year course. Overall, with the very recent implementation of this new engineering-mathematics syllabus, early, informal indications suggest that the redesign has been quite effective in terms of appropriate  mapping  onto the student  school-level mathematics background and abilities, helping with a good transition to university-level mathematics education in Engineering.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0016</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Evaluating Postgraduate student' Perceptions of ALL: findings from a longitudinal study</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Gill Cooke</u>, Phillip Lewis, Irene Glendinning <em>Coventry University, Coventry, UK</em></p><p>activities Led Learning (ALL) was introduced in a postgraduate module, Management of Quality, during the 2010-11 academic year designed to improve student engagement. The implementation of ALL centred on a "passport" concept which required the student to engage with the module both prior to and during the contact sessions. This system encouraged more effective engagement, through active participation and interaction during the contact time. student were required to work on pre-determined activities in groups and communicate with other student about what they had learned. Since its' introduction the module has been incrementally refined in response to evidence and feedback. For the first two years the changes were only implemented and evaluated for full time (largely international) student. In the third year, the concept was extended to include part time (predominantly UK student in full-time employment) to explore and evaluate transfer-ability. The part time version was based on the same concept with organisational differences to account for the different delivery timescale.  All module iterations were carefully monitored and evaluated using a qualitative research design and anonymous surveys. Findings demonstrated that the increased engagement led to improved student satisfaction and deep learning, achieved through the introduction of constructive alignment between the activities and assessments. The data also demonstrated that the concept could be adapted to suit a different cohort type and delivery schedule.This paper presents the findings from this longitudinal study. The authors believe this concept is transferable to other subjects, institutions and situations to help improve the postgraduate student experience.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0018</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Multidisciplinary Learning Affordances of a Science-Based Virtual World Environment</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Technology in Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Katrina Nordstr</u><sup>1</sup>, Pekka Qvist<sup>2</sup>, Tuomas Kangasniemi<sup>1</sup>, Sonja Palom?<sup>1</sup>, Sebastian Olkinuora<sup>1</sup>, Marko N?i<sup>1</sup>, Olli Natri<sup>1</sup>, Jenni Sepp?n<sup>3</sup>, Paulus Artimo<sup>3</sup>, Pekka Joensuu<sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Aalto University, Espoo, 00076 Aalto, Finland,<sup> 2</sup>Metaverstas Ltd., Turku, Finland,<sup> 3</sup>Helsinki University, Helsinki, Finland</em></p><p>Virtual world (VW) spaces are the embodiment of future learning environments with user-generated content allowing for the maximization of capacity for iterative design in response to user feedback and changing social, environmental, and educational contexts. VWs have many significant advantages compared to real-life learning spaces, and foster the digital literacies necessary to participate in the evolving workplace or study environment in a modern knowledge-based economy. Accordingly we have designed and tested the instructional use of a virtual laboratory, LabLife3D, in Second Life, to bridge the gap between theory and practice. We have built 5 virtual laboratory exercises in biotechnology and chemistry; a virus isolation experiment, a laboratory safety tutorial, organic chemistry decarboxylation reactions and vacuum distillation, and a molecular biology simulation. We present the design process, the views of student and teachers on barriers and enablers to learning in VWs. Some 40 student took part in the testing and 18 teachers have been interviewed on the role of facilitation and the ease of use of digital technology in teaching and learning. We have also experimented with collecting quantitative data on student decisions in the virtual environment. Such data consists of clicks and events triggered by the clicks, time tags of all the actions, compositions of the used substances, and needed actions. student gave very positive feedback on the learning experiences, but teachers were more hesitant to embrace new technology. Thus, there is a need for generating clear instructional "toolboxes" and facilitation roles for teachers in digital environments.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0019</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Training of Academic Staff for Engineering Education: A  Programme for Developing Teaching and Learning at University</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Continuing Engineering Education and Lifelong learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Monika Rummler</u> <em>TU Berlin, Berlin, Berlin, Germany</em></p><p></p><p></p><p>Technische Universit?Berlin (TUB), one of the biggest technical university in Germany, is qualifying about 30 000 student. Hundreds of student in lectures and courses make teaching and learning often ineffective and unsatisfying. This situation is very demanding for the teaching staff, the more that most of them have neither previous didactic nor pedagogic training for their teaching tasks.</p><p>Therefore, we train teaching staff at TUB to develop their teaching competences. In addition to about 300 full-time professors, it comprises nearly 2500<b> </b>research and teaching assistants, normally contracted for 5 years. Besides working on their doctoral thesis, they are obliged to teach at least 4 hours per week.</p><p></p><p>The crucial question is: How can teaching staff be trained motivational and effectively for innovative teaching formats to foster interactive learning in this environment? How a new teaching and learning culture can be implemented successfully?</p><p></p><p>Our solution is to develop teaching competences theoretically and practically. We focus on improving the quality of teaching and learning as well as the satisfaction of teachers and learners. Our training programme  teaching and learning  (accredited by the German Association for Academic Development) is complemented by tailor-made offers according to teachers  individual needs. The long-term goal is to qualify all teaching staff during all phases of their teaching career corresponding with the impact of life long learning and professional supportive structures at university and in faculties.</p><p></p><p>The paper will describe and analyse the curriculum for the qualification. A desirable brand of competences in teaching-profile will be outlined.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0020</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Evaluation of Innovative Teaching and Learning Projects in Engineering Education</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Quality Assurance and Accreditation</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Petra Nikol</u> <em>TU Berlin, Berlin, Berlin, Germany</em></p><p>The evaluation of lectures, exercise classes and tutorials is getting more and more important in the university context due to quality aspects. This is particularly true for <b><i>tu wimi <sup>plus</sup></i></b>, which is one among 8 project-lines at TU Berlin, funded by the German Federal Ministry of Education and Research to provide better study conditions and to improve the quality of teaching and learning. Currently, it provides support for 7 research and teaching assistants in 9 innovative teaching projects at thematically very different chairs (e.g. electrical engineering, mathematics or mechanics) on how to design and implement subject-specific teaching curricula in the respective fields. In order to augment interdisciplinary and student-centred approach, a variety of instruments is used such as the development of innovative teaching and learning projects, within which problem-oriented or e-learning-supported methods are applied more frequently.</p><p>However, when it comes to evaluation we need to find out how didactically innovative teaching and learning projects should be evaluated and how they are perceived by student compared to ex-cathedra teaching.</p><p>Addressing these questions, we developed a questionnaire which matches the learning objectives of the lectures. It focuses on a self-evaluation of the learning activities student perform in class rather than concentrating on their satisfaction with the lecture. The effectiveness of this method was tested in a pilot study in4 of our teaching projects during the winter term 2013/2014.</p><p>The paper describes the concept of the questionnaire and its sections. First findings of our pilot study will be presented during the conference.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0021</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Early Career Female Engineers: Influences and Challenges</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Issues of Gender and Diversity</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>John Davies</u><sup>1</sup>, Abbie Jones<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Coventry University, Coventry, UK,<sup> 2</sup>WSP, Birmingham, UK</em></p><p>The gender balance within engineering is a current concern, particularly in the UK. There is a great deal of interest in determining why fewer girls take STEM subjects in education and in identifying barriers to females studying and practising engineering. </p><p>This study chose as its focus early career female engineers, typically between graduation and professional qualification. It was felt that this group gave a particularly valuable perspective, since at this important early stage in their careers they are able to recall key influences on career decision-making, and pinpoint with fresh eyes significant challenges in the profession.</p><p>Ten participants were interviewed as part of the study. Key themes were developed by the researcher throughout the study, focusing on the main influences on participants' choice of engineering as a subject and career, and the current challenges they face today.</p><p>This paper describes the study, and presents the perspectives, ideas and recommendations of the early career female engineers interviewed. Key findings are that participants were largely influenced in their choice of engineering by family or personal experiences, but generally felt let down by the careers advice, and awareness of the engineering industry, at school. Many participants felt that stereotyped images of engineers still exist outside the industry. They also indicated that the type of engineering company greatly affects the type of challenges a female engineers might face. Participants felt that active promotion of STEM subjects within education is important, but not necessarily aimed only at girls.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0022</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Supporting Engineering student at the start of their university course: an industry-university collaboration to provide tailored online mathematics resources.</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Maths in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Stephen Lee</u><sup>1</sup>, Michael Peters<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Mathematics in Education and Industry, Trowbridge, UK,<sup> 2</sup>Aston University, Birmingham, UK</em></p><p>Mathematics in Education and Industry (MEI), a small, independent, charitable UK curriculum development body, collaborated with Aston University to establish a tailored online support course of mathematics materials for several groups of undergraduate engineering student. These student were studying for a Foundation Degree in either Power Engineering or Gas Transmission. They were heterogeneous in terms of their skills and knowledge of mathematics. Many of them had not studied mathematics for some years and others expressed concerns about the level of mathematics they would encounter at Aston University. student would access the online materials in the weeks prior to beginning lectures at the university and they continued to have access throughout their first year of their study. This approach was taken in order to reduce student anxiety and to manage their expectations of studying mathematics at university level.</p><p>This paper gives an outline of the creation of the mathematics support  course' produced within a Moodle Virtual Learning Environment, before detailing the student who used the materials. Feedback from the project is presented and comparisons made with feedback received from a similar pilot course for STEM student.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0023</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Upgraded Practical Training for student of Nuclear Sciences at CTU-FNSPE</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Physics in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Ladislav Musilek</u>, Jan Cepila, Katerina Cubova, Rudolf Klepacek, Dusan Kobylka, Petr Prusa <em>Czech Technical University in Prague, Faculty of Nuclear Sciences and Physical Engineering, Praha 1, Czech Republic</em></p><p></p><p>The CTU-FNSPE in Prague is the only university institution in the country that teaches and develops a broad range of studies in the field of nuclear sciences. The Faculty has its own small nuclear reactor and a small tokamak. The rapid development of nuclear physics and chemistry, and of their applications, and also ongoing efforts achieve the highest possible levels of nuclear and radiation safety, have led to a need for advanced practical training for student. A project was therefore applied for within the framework of the Prague Adaptability Operational Programme, supported by European funding. This project aims to improve the quality of studies in educational institutions in Prague, and has been used to innovate the laboratories for practical training of student at five departments of the Faculty. A total of 23 exercises for measuring and evaluating various quantities have been upgraded or newly prepared, ranging from the characteristics of nuclear reactor kinetics, through the design of the electronic circuits for nuclear measurements, ionising radiation spectrometry, measurement of the absorbed dose, detection of radioactive contamination, to topics such as the use of radiation diffraction in the study of materials. This paper deals with the system for practical training of student of nuclear sciences at the Faculty, and shows how the result of the project have been helping to refine the practical training of student. The practical exercises will be offered both for student of FNSPE and other educational institutions, and for in-service training and life-long learning.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0024</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>The application of Repertory Grid interview method for improving the identification and understanding of competencies required for engineering practice</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Education al Research Methods</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Mohd Nazri Mahmud</u>, Tom Ridgman <em>University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK</em></p><p></p><p></p><p> Educating engineers through outcome-based education requires the identification of competencies required for engineering practice. One of the ways in which such competencies can be identified is by engaging with practising engineers through interviews. During interviews, engineers are asked to describe competencies required for various aspects of engineering practice. However, there are at least two main limitations in such interviews. First, practising engineers often find it difficult to articulately describe and explain part of competencies that are implicit [1]. Second, interviewers often find it difficult to accurately interpret words and phrases used for competency descriptions [2]. Interview methods that can improve the identification and understanding of competencies required have therefore been called for.</p><p>This paper describes an interview method that can help interviewers in identifying part of competencies that are implicit, and in interpreting words and phrases used by interviewees. We adopt, adapt and apply the Repertory Grid Technique (RGT) method for interviewing practising engineers. It is found that such approach can facilitate the elicitation of competencies that are implicit to the interviewees. It can also help in accessing personal meanings of words and phrases used by them.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0025</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Teachas you preach: Professionalizing teaching assistants in engineering within the 2020 context</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal">Inge Van Hemelrijck<sup>1
                    ,2</sup>, Elsje Londers<sup>1
                    ,2</sup>, Yolande Berbers<sup>1</sup>, <u>Laura De Geyter</u><sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Faculty of Engineering, KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium,<sup> 2</sup>Leuven Engineering and Science Education Center (LESEC), Leuven, Belgium</em></p><p>At KU Leuven, practice sessions are traditionally the responsibility of teaching assistants, typically PhD student with an additional teaching assignment. The Faculty of Engineering attaches great importance to the role of the TAs since practice sessions are an indispensable tool in a student's learning process. After all, these additional contact moments serve as the necessary bridge between the theory taught during the lectures and the practice these student will face during their exams and in their future careers. Since many teaching assistants struggled with coaching these practice sessions, the Faculty of Engineering at the KU Leuven introduced an educational training programme for PhD student in 2005. In 2013, this programme was evaluated through a questionnaire of 400 TAs, combined with focus groups with some 20 assistants of 5 deliberately chosen courses. These revealed the specific needs of these teaching assistants that will constitute the building blocks of the new training programme.</p><p>In this paper, we will present the blueprint for the new TA training that will draw on the 'teach as you preach' principle, thus enabling the TAs to get acquainted with new didactical techniques that will enhance and facilitate the learning process of their student. This programme will consist of a number of sessions that revolve around different teaching formats, designed to reflect the educational practice of the TAs. These training sessions will focus on the principles of flipped teaching, dealing with frequently occurring problems, activating student and the implementation of modern technology in the teaching practice.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0026</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>A Engineering Imagination Training Paradigm based on Conceptual Combination Theory</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Continuing Engineering Education and Lifelong learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Poster</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Ruey-Yun Horng</u><sup>3</sup>, Ching-Wen Wang<sup>2</sup>, Chien-Tao Li<sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>National Chiao Tung University, Hsinchu, Taiwan,<sup> 2</sup>National Chung Hsing University, Taichung, Taiwan,<sup> 3</sup>National Chung Hsing University, Taichung, Taiwan</em></p><p>This study aims to propose a conceptual combination training paradigm for enhancing engineering imagination. Conceptual combination refers to joining of two or more than two concepts to produce new concepts. It is proposed to be the cognitive process underlying human imagination. However, not all ideas produced from conceptual combination are original. Factors that increase the chance of producing original ideas from conceptual combination include: 1. a random process to attract disparate and remote concepts to be considered together, 2. the concepts are conceived in a relatively abstract level, 3. The type of interpretation used to combine the concepts meaningfully, and 4. The selection criteria so that original ideas can be retained for further consideration. For enhancing engineering creativity, a priming paradigm that incorporates the above four factors is proposed. In the training, participants will be instructed about different types of interpretation that can be used to combine two unrelated concepts. Then, several sessions of conceptual combination practice would be administered. During practice, noun-noun pairs that are formed by unrelated concepts of different ontological categories are presented, and participants have to generate a new idea using a specific type of interpretation. The noun-noun pairs can vary freely in terms of the level of abstractness, or domain knowledge. It is expected that the training will facilitate the random process in participants  thinking, and their ability to join two or more than two remote concepts together. It is predicted that such practice would prime for more original ideas in engineering design tasks.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0028</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Industrial Leadership Requirements- qualifications promoting competitiveness</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Pia Lappalainen</u> <em>Aalto University, Espoo, Finland</em></p><p>European higher engineering education has a solid tradition in imparting an education that equips engineering graduates with a broad base of knowledge, skills and attitudes pivotal to success in industrial processes. And yet, despite the changing global conditions calling for new approach to industrial leadership, leadership training as part of higher education, especially in technical fields, has remained unappreciated. To better meet industrial competence requirements in engineering education, the Accreditation Board of Engineering and Technology has recently extended its accreditation criteria to leadership, "leading engineering endeavours" but concrete efforts to conceptualize effective leadership and define leader competences still remain modest, hindering the related curriculum development. This paper sheds light on industrial leadership requirements and the related implications for pedagogy integrating leadership skills and competences into higher engineering education. The present study embarked on a quantitative empirical effort to identify leader requirements in engineering communities. Specifically, the study divided leader qualifications into six categories: 1) substantive knowledge, 2) personality (motifs), 3) emotive skills, 4) communication skills, 5) cultural skills, and 6) values and attitudes. Under such a definition of leader capabilities, leader qualifications were further divided into 80 skills, abilities or personality traits.</p><p>The result from a sample of 462 respondents to an online survey indicate that such emotive skills and personality dimensions that form the foundation for self-leadership are prioritized highest in leader evaluations, both as viewed by managers and subordinates.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0029</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>PLACIS: Active learning and teaching through industrial, international and at-a-distance collaborative projects</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Poster</p><p class="MsoNormal">Alexis Fran?s, <u>Antoine Lanthony</u> <em>SUPMECA, Saint-Ouen, France</em></p><p>PLACIS is a project funded by the French National Agency for Research under "Investments for the future" program. PLACIS started in September 2012 and will finish in August 2016. The project was presented at the 41st SEFI Conference in the paper "PLACIS: International Inter-University Collaborative Training Platform in Systems Engineering". Since this paper, PLACIS gained in maturity: new student' projects, new partners, but also development of new tools and use of PLACIS as a base for a new Erasmus+ project.</p><p> All these aspects make us able to see the first achievements of what is the main PLACIS goal: not only to train student to become classic engineers, but to train student to become systems engineers, able to understand multidisciplinary issues, to work in teams, with people from different cultures and, more generally, to be actors of their curricula and to move easily in today's and tomorrow's industrial world.</p><p> Moreover, one of our goals is to engage into active training of teachers, because we think that trying to reach the student without trying to reach the teachers could lead to failures. This will be done in the new Erasmus+ project.</p><p> Our poster presents PLACIS through its objectives, paths and tools, ongoing development and main result. It makes clear how PLACIS projects work, what student gain from them and what will be the future steps for PLACIS.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0030</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Developing an Online Course: Challenges and Enablers</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Technology in Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Aikaterini Bagiati</u> <em>Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA, USA</em></p><p></p><p>Innovations in teaching methods and educational technology, combined with the advent of Internet, advancement in infrastructure that allows for connectivity at a global level, and developments in open access, have been leading scholars to rethink the learning process and the opportunities for new educational settings worldwide. Technology now allows professors to transfer even more information outside the classroom enabling them to flip their classroom and use in-class time in a different manner. Building on these trends, MIT established the Office of Digital Learning (ODL) in 2012. The mission of the ODL is to help the MIT community lead the world in education by creating, using and levering learning technology and digital instructional content. MITx is a constituent organization of ODL, aiming to support development of MIT-quality online courses, and to further understanding of best practices in digital learning. Some of the online courses developed by MITx have been designed as Massive Online Open Courses (MOOCs) offered to a global audience, while others are still only used within MIT to enhance residential education. Through the end of 2013, 15 MOOCs were offered globally through the EdX platform and 23 online courses were offered at a residential level within the flipped-classroom framework. Through this study we hope to understand the process faculty members and their teams go through while developing their online courses, and identify challenges and enablers. Data stemming from 10 faculty members, research staff and graduate student who participated in the online course development are presented in this paper.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0031</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Does increasing student activities and reducing lecturing improve learning outcome in courses?</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Lars Peter Jensen</u> <em>Aalborg University, Aalborg, Denmark</em></p><p>Aalborg University has used Problem Based Learning since 1974. The primary model is big projects (15 ECTS) each semester solved in student groups. The rest of the study time the student follow courses where exercises is solved together in the student groups to enhance peer learning in courses. Traditionally courses have been 50% lecturing and 50% exercises. As an experiment it was decided to change that in the autumn 2013 trying to activate the student more by decreasing the lecturing and use more time and effort on exercises followed up by a reflective dialogue with the student about lessons learnt. The setup of the traditional and the new version of the course is explained and the effects of the change analyzed by comparing two cohorts of first semester Software Engineering and Computer Science student. The course is aimed at improving the potential of freshmen student project work helping them to develop their skills in cooperation, learning and project management. After the semester each student group write a process analysis where they reflect on these issues and come up with ideas to improve their performance in the next project. The effect of the changes in the course is analyzed by comparing both the written Process Analysis and individual answers from the student to relevant exam questions taken from a written exam of the course. The result show that less lecturing doesn't decrease the student's skills in the subjects and more exercises and reflections don't improve the skills either.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0032</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Achieving generic competences through a cross-disciplinary research based course in Arctic Technology</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Gunvor M. Kirkelund</u><sup>1</sup>, Claus T. Hansen<sup>2</sup>, Pernille E. Jensen<sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>DTU Civil Engineering, Techincal University of Denmark, Kgs. Lyngby, Denmark,<sup> 2</sup>DTU Mechanical Engineering, Kgs. Lyngby, Denmark</em></p><p>A cross-disciplinary research based 15 ECTS course in Arctic Technology is offered to engineering student regardless of study programme. The main focus for the student is on a specific research project formed around a 3 weeks field period in Greenland. The teaching activities focus on developing engineering competences such as project planning and management, working in a different culture as well as both oral and written communication skills, while the student are studying a topic relevant to their study programme in the new Arctic setting. The student work through 3 semesters with their chosen project, with preparation of field work in the spring, practical field work in the summer and project work and reporting in the autumn. It is essential that the student take ownership of and manage their own project, with the course responsible as a guide to the Arctic context and the project supervisor as the scientific topic specific guide. During the course, the student are offered different feedback options on their work and progress. To be able to assess all student, the learning objectives and feedback are generically focussed rather than topic specific. It is clearly seen by the learning outcome and assessment that student who use the feedback options actively are more successful in achieving both the scientific and the generic competences than the student who do not. The student evaluate the course as being highly motivating for further learning and they get confident by successfully having executed a research based project in a new context.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0033</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Developing and Conducting Entrepreneurship Education for Engineering student<em>- Lessons learned whileeducating student through entrepreneurship</em></strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Either</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Mette Lindahl Thomassen</u> <em>VIA University College, Horsens, Denmark</em></p><p><b>Abstract theme: </b>Curriculum development<b></b></p><p><b>Abstract</b></p><p><b>Purpose:</b></p><p>As a natural reaction to the increased societal and governmental interest in entrepreneurship, the offering, conducting and research of entrepreneurship education has become a focal pointat university.   </p><p>The purpose of this paper is to put the topic of entrepreneurship education into an engineering educational context and propose an answer the question "How can entrepreneurship be taught to engineering student?" This paper is primarily written for other lectures with the purpose of sharing experiences in an attempt to further develop the field of entrepreneurship education in engineering departments and secondary as food for thought for decision makers regarding curriculum content in the aforementioned departments</p><p><b>Design/methodology/approach:</b></p><p>In order to investigate the research question a literature review is done combined with an prospective case study, serving both as an illustrative case and as a source of empirical data.</p><p><b>Findings:</b></p><p>There are numerous ways of developing and conducting entrepreneurship education varying in purpose ansform. Education through entrepreneurship has proven purposeful in terms of developing student likely to display entrepreneurial behaviour in the future, but educating through entrepreneurship poses a number of challenges both in relation to the frames of higher educational institutes and in terms of facilitating group of causal trained student through an effectuation process.  </p><p><b>Originality/Value:</b></p><p>The paper at hand testify to the value of entrepreneurship education but at the same time shed light on some of the challenges associated with it. Owning the question of how to best solve the problems?  </p><p><b>Papertype: </b>Empirical paper</p><p><b>Session Format: </b>Research Discussion Session</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0034</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Experiential learning as a method to enhance experiential teaching </strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Pernille Andersson</u>, Claus Thorp Hansen <em>Technical University of Denmark, Kgs. Lyngby Copenhagen, Denmark</em></p><p>Crucial for success in Engineering Education (EE) to educate engineers equipped with the knowledge, skills and attitudes they need to meet the challenges they will face as professionals is that faculty has the right competences to, and understanding about, how to enhance learning. One of the roads forward is to use student centred and active teaching methods. Even if the development of EE in this direction has been going on for several years, still it is hard to make a sustain shift in learning culture at many university. A teacher training programme for experienced teachers has recently been developed at DTU where the aim is through experiential learning learn the participants about and how to use experiential learning in courses. The overall strategy follows the steps in the learning circle of Kolb in a pure way, staring with the participants' analysis of their own teaching experiences and of their student' perception of the teaching provided. This is followed by theoretical input about teaching and learning in higher education in the stage of abstract conceptualisation. On the background of those stages the participants construct a new course design and suggest an implementation plan of the revisions. In this paper we describe this new teacher training programme. The participants' experiences and learning outcomes will also be discussed mirrored in what research in the field. Finally, we reflect upon whether a teacher training programme of this kind fulfils its overall purpose to impact development of teaching practice and to what extent.<i>  </i></p><p><i></i></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0035</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>How inquiry project-based instruction affect the vocational high school student' learning performance</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Poster</p><p class="MsoNormal">Shiang-Yao Liu<sup>1</sup>, Chien-Cheng Tsai<sup>2</sup>, <u>Chi-Ming Lai</u><sup>3</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Graduate Institute of Science Education, National Taiwan Normal University, Taipei, Taiwan,<sup> 2</sup>Division of Civil Engineering, National Tainan Vocational High School, Tainan, Taiwan,<sup> 3</sup>Department of Civil Engineering, National Cheng Kung University, Tainan, Taiwan</em></p><p>This study is part of a collaborative program between university and vocational senior high school for improving teaching and learning in engineering courses. One class of student who attended the course of "surveying practicum" was observed to evaluate the effectiveness of teaching improvement. In the practicum, student are usually guided to follow the standard operational process or cook-book like protocol to make rigid and precise measurement. After gaining exposure to project-based instructional strategies, the teacher designed a series of surveying tasks, including traverse surveying and longitudinal section surveying that allow student to discuss the methods and procedures with peers and find out the resolutions on their own. Each group of student then presented their design and result after carrying out surveys on campus. It was fairly surprising to the teacher that student generated two effective methods with one similar to that in the textbook and the other one new. Multiple sources of quantitative and qualitative data were collected during the course to explore any changes on student' views of scientific inquiry and perceptions of learning. Analyses of the pre- and post- tests collected from the modified Views of Science Inquiry (VOSI) questionnaire indicated that student' understanding about scientific inquiry has improved after the course (average score increased from 7.45 to 9.28 based on the scoring criteria developed in this study). Qualitative data through triangulation revealed that student find this innovative instruction enjoyable and experiential because it can initiate self-directed learning and creativity.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0036</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>The effects of imagination on engineering design performance</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Education al Research Methods</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Poster</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Ching-Wen Wang</u><sup>2</sup>, Chia-Ying Lu<sup>1</sup>, Ruey-Yun Horng<sup>3</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>National Chung Hsing University, Taichung, Taiwan,<sup> 2</sup>National Taiwan University, Taipei, Taiwan,<sup> 3</sup>National Chiao Tung University, Hsinchu, Taiwan</em></p><p>Variable needs and advancement in technology promote the continuous innovations on technological products. As imagination is the key component in creativity, how to facilitate imagination in product design and development becomes an important part of engineering design education. This study defines imagination in terms of the ability for conceptual combination, and examines the role of imagination on engineering design performance through a creativity competition. There were three stages in the creativity competition. Three scholars and two design experts evaluated the competition, and the evaluation criteria included innovation, subject conceptualization and content clarity, as well as strategy for competition and creative marketing. In the first stage, 120 dyads participated. They were asked to creatively conceptualize three topics. In the second stage, 45 dyads were chosen and participated in a one-day imagination workshop. The training included imagination and conceptual combination, design concept and application, and case studies on imagination and innovation. These groups were asked to submit their proposals on a new innovative product or marketing strategy. In the third stage, 15 dyads were chosen and presentedtheir proposals. The participants of this study were the 45 dyads in the second stage, whom were asked to take the imagination measure. The result found that participants' imagination ability had significant role on the design performance, and the 15 dyads that went into the final competition showed higher imagination. Therefore, the study suggests that engineering design education should emphasize the training on creativity and imagination and include them in professional classes.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0037</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Developing a Creativity-enhanced PBL for Inspiring Future Hydraulic Engineers</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal">Ya-Ting Yang<sup>1</sup>, <u>Hsiao-Wen Wang</u><sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>The Institute of Education, National Cheng-Kung University, Tainan, Taiwan,<sup> 2</sup>Department of Hydraulic and Ocean Engineering, National Cheng-Kung University, Tainan, Taiwan</em></p><p>Taiwan is in a seismically active zone and frequently experiences tropical storms and large variations in precipitation. In order to prevent and manage the consequences of earthquakes, typhoons, and excessive rainfall, hydraulic engineering education in Taiwan must be directed towards practical and relevant learning while also fostering higher order thinking skills, such as creativity and problem solving. Since project-based learning (PBL) provides contextualized and authentic learning, which has been demonstrated to foster higher order thinking while promoting acquisition of content-area knowledge, this project applies PBL to hydraulic engineering education. A PBL curriculum was designed to emphasize real-world problems, which enabled student to actively explore the project for the cause and process, to explain the cause and effect and solution, and to extensively apply the knowledge they learn. By doing so, this curriculum can enhance learning motivation and academic performance. In this study, we adopted creativity-enhanced PBL with the aim to foster the creativity and problem-solving skills necessary for innovation and excellence in the learners  future professional careers as hydraulic engineers. The study will adopt a pretest and post-test quasi-experimental design. Over a 16-week intervention, the control group will receive traditional instruction while the experimental group will receive PBL instruction. Analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) will be used to compare the learning outcomes of the two research groups. This study will explore how different teaching strategies influence student  creativity and problem-solving skills and, at the same time, hydraulic engineering knowledge.</p><p>Keyword: hydraulic engineering, project-based learning, creativity, problem-solving.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0039</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Engineering and network analysis</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal">Rossella Pozzi, <u>Carlo No</u>, Fernanda Strozzi <em>LIUC University, Castellanza, Italy</em></p><p>Reports on the future of engineering by the National Academy of Engineering describe the economy in which engineers will work as strongly influenced by the global marketplace for engineering services. Globalization together with more and more frequent interaction will drive to increasing complexity the systems industrial engineers will deal with. Nowadays, systems as well as communities and computer networks are represented as complex networks, and complex networks theory represents a tool for effectively studying and understanding them.</p><p>The present work presents the learning experience of four work groups of Engineering student of LIUC University facing network analysis for the first time. In particular, each work group is free to apply the network analysis to a topic belonging to its area of interest. In order to respond the research questions proposed, each group apply the most suitable measures of the complex networks theory, and the obtained result are outlined. Last, the present paper points out the managerial implications recommended by the work groups, advised by the authors, due to the network analysis result.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0040</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Authentic Assessments of Teaching Skills</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Quality Assurance and Accreditation</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Thomas Olsson</u><sup>1</sup>, Bj??Badersten<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Faculty of Engineering, Lund University, Lund, Sweden,<sup> 2</sup>Faculty of Social Sciences, Lund University, Lund, Sweden</em></p><p>In this <i>Research Discussion Session</i> we would like to discuss a collaborative project, that is carried out by the Faculty of Engineering and the Faculty of Social Sciences at Lund University, with the ambition to develop research based supplementary methods to evaluate and assess teachers' teaching skills. We are well aware that such methods can only demonstrate selected perspectives of the complexity of teaching skills, but could form an important attempt to capture a more authentic picture of parts of what represents good teaching.</p><p>We build the development on our research about rewarding and assessing teaching skills and pedagogical competence (Olsson and Rox?008; Olsson and Rox?012; Olsson and Rox?013; Larsson, Anderberg and Olsson 2014). We will examine the possibility to develop tests based on case studies. It could be cases concerning different types of problematic teaching situations or aspects of evaluation and assessment. Another suggestion could be analyses of authentic teaching situations (described or filmed). Further proposals to investigate could be planning of teaching and learning activities (at programme level, course level or class level); discussions about learning hurdles (Shulman 1986) and the content of teaching (what, how, why. We will also consider the possibility of combining a specific task with a short presentation (in an authentic lesson/lecture form).</p><p>Our initial draft is to build assessment of teaching skills on reflection in action (Sch??983) and actions that question current assumptions and conditions for the implementation of teaching (Argyris and Sch??974).</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0041</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong> Enabling and supporting quality assurance in a major engineering faculty'</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Quality Assurance and Accreditation</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Val?e Wyns</u>, Elsje Londers, Inge Van Hemelrijck, Yolande Berbers <em>KULeuven, Leuven, Belgium</em></p><p></p><p>The Faculty of Engineering Science at the KU Leuven invests greatly in quality assurance. However, because of the complex nature of the faculty, which comprises 22 programme of varying level, student numbers and characteristics, a thoroughly efficient approach to quality assurance is necessary. The paper presented will focus on the process of formulating learning outcomes and performing parallel curriculum mappings throughout the engineering faculty.</p><p>The education staff members formulated a three-step approach to improve uniformity of learning outcomes and ECTS-files, resulting in the harmonization of the curriculum. The first step consists of translating the learning outcomes of each programme into the same  framework', namely ACQA (Academic Competences and Quality Assurance). Educational developers assist each programme in reformulating their learning outcomes. The second step consists of an extensive online curriculum mapping, registering to which outcomes each course contributes. The mapping provides a view of the presence of attention paid to each learning outcome. A third step entails a thorough check of all ECTS-files. Each professor receives personalized suggestions on how they can improve their files. We compiled a customized checklist so the check-up can proceed as fluently as possible.</p><p>After these three steps, the review of the faculty's curriculum is facilitated greatly by the synchronized learning outcomes and the easily accessible curriculum mappings. Adopting the ACQA-framework also proved to be a starting point for the exchange of experiences and reflection by professors and teaching assistants.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0042</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Situation in Engineering university of Applied Science in Oulu and Eindhoven to Teach Methods to Achieve Innovations in Businesses</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Hannu P?alo</u><sup>1</sup>, Hay Geraedts<sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Oulu University of Applied Sciences, Oulu, Finland,<sup> 2</sup>Fontys University of Applied Sciences Eindhoven, Eindhoven, The Netherlands</em></p><p><b>Situation in Engineering Education in Oulu and Eindhoven to Teach Methods to Achieve Innovations in Businesses</b></p><p>Hannu P?alo and Hay Geraedts</p><p>Hannu P?alo, Oulu University of applied Sciences, Oulu, Finland, hannu.paatalo@oamk.fi</p><p>Hay Geraedts, Fontys University of applied Sciences, Eindhoven, the Netherlands, hgm.geraedts@fontys.nl</p><p>            </p><p>The importance of teaching engineering student innovation development is commonly clearly understood. It is essential to achieve products which are attractive and profitable in the market. To achieve this, an institute of engineering education has to provide student with needed knowledge, skills and attitudes including both technical and business orientation. This is important especially for SME's.</p><p>Traditionally, education of engineering provides student with basic understanding how to solve common technical problems. However companies need wider view to achieve new products. university of Applied Science in Oulu and Eindhoven want to research what is the today's educational situation for this aim, to find criteria to improve the content of the educational system, and to improve the educational system.</p><p>Important stakeholders are teachers and student within the institute but also key-persons in companies. The research is realized by questionnaires and interviews from which a current situation can be found. The research will also include the opinion of management who give possibilities to change the curriculum. By this research more insight will be presented about how to re-design a current curriculum.The research will act as basis for this discussion in SEFI-conference about formulating a curriculum that includes elements for wide-ranging knowledge and skills to achieve innovations especially in SME's.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0043</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Industry and engineering education interacting in an interregional project - a Flanders' perspective</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Continuing Engineering Education and Lifelong learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Either</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Jos Knockaert</u><sup>1</sup>, Geert De Lepeleer<sup>2</sup>, Tony Stevens<sup>2</sup>, Philippe Saey<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Ghent University, Ghent, Belgium,<sup> 2</sup>KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium</em></p><p>The Interreg-IVa 2-Seas project i-MOCCA ("interregional MObility and Competence Centres in Automation") concentrates on two fast evolving topics: industrial data communication and embedded control. Both require high-end training of practising engineers in industry and demonstrators illustrating proof-of-principle of emerging technology. The i-MOCCA project aims to develop competence centres in different university in the coastal regions of the UK, France and Flanders, Belgium. The "triple helix model" incorporating university and knowledge centres, government and professional organizations, and the private (industry) sector, is regarded by the EU as very important for the "knowledge based economy". From the beginning, the i-MOCCA project partners have established numerous contacts with the private sector via courses, MSc final year projects delivering use cases for industry and for? relevant laboratory exercises, lectures, ... Cooperation with government and professional organizations is established by funding, dissemination, broad communication, Essential for interregional cooperation between the i-MOCCA partners is the use of "common basic equipment", facilitating efficient cooperation and joint development. This enables staff mobility avoiding movement of equipment. On "internal i-MOCCA conferences" intermediate work packages and result are discussed. On more informal "technical days", work in progress (demonstrators, measurements, ...) is shown and discussed in an interactive way. Finished courses are exchanged (and used on the same equipment), and - if relevant - taught to each other. In the full paper, the above mentioned items are discussed in detail. Industry participation, the numbers of reached engineers, the influence on curriculum development, and emerging student exchanges between project partners are also presented.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0044</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Design of an interdisciplinary engineering elective scoped around collaboration with Small Medium Sized enterprises (SME)</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Industry involvement in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal">Nynne Christiansen, <u>Maja Pontoppidan</u>, Mai-Mai Ulrich <em>The Technical University of Denmark, Ballerup, Denmark</em></p><p>DTU Diplom a department of the Technical University of Denmark, educating industry oriented Bachelors of Engineering. One of the goals is to strengthen the collaboration with small and medium-sized enterprises (SME's). Some of the traditional barriers for industry collaboration, especially with SMEs, are difference in time horizon and the difference between the high-tech research case that university look for, and the practical often low-tech solutions that the businesses are looking for.</p><p>In designing the course SME Innovation and Intrapreneurship that focus especially on small and micro-sized companies, we have tried to create a match between the company need for short, result oriented innovation projects and the structured professional and interdisciplinary learning goals for a future bachelor of engineering. The course is structured around a shorter project-period of challenging the problem proposed by the company and building the relations among the student necessary to generate innovation and a longer project period dedicated solving the engineering challenge as well as merging the commercial and technical aspects of the innovation process.</p><p> We have used the CDIO (Conceive-Design-Implement-Operate) pedagogical framework to design the project. The paper includes considerations on design and experiences with SME collaboration running the first course this spring, where the most important learnings are:</p><ul><li>Companies and projects should be chosen carefully, and expectation adjustment is essential.</li><li>It is a benefit for the student to get to work in an interdisciplinary context.</li><li>A sponsorship fee raises the engagement for the University, Company. It is necessary to improve the Student sense of obligation</li></ul><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0045</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Higher Education Research and Engineering Education Research: Comparative Perspectives</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Education al Research Methods</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Lars Geschwind</u><sup>1</sup>, Anette Kolmos<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>KTH Royal Institute of Technology, Stockholm, Sweden,<sup> 2</sup>Aalborg University, Aalborg, Denmark</em></p><p>Higher education is a sector of growing importance in many societies, which is one of the reasons why it increasingly has found itself the object of research the last decades. Consequently, the number of publications including e.g. peer reviewed journals and meeting places such as conferences and seminars have increased dramatically. Engineering education, as one of the major sub-fields within higher education has, similar to other professional fields, developed its own journals, meeting places and traditions. Both fields have been described as interdisciplinary or multidisciplinary comprising of a mix of disciplinary perspectives and approach. However, increasingly the fields have been established, not only in terms of journals and conferences, but also shown in chairs, dedicated research units etc. In this paper we compare these two different yet related research fields: higher education research and engineering education research. We ask the following research questions: Which research issues are in focus? Which theories and methods are used? How are the result reported? What is the relation to educational practice? We will build our analytical model on developed taxonomies and an analysis of journals, which we have adjusted to the empirical field of both higher education and engineering education. We have chosen four leading journals representing the two fields and analyse the last ten latest online published articles in 2013. The preliminary result indicate differences in the theoretical approach, instrument development, and closeness to the empirical field and impact for practice.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0046</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Tuition fees and attractiveness of engineering education</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Attractiveness of Engineering</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Katriina Schrey-Niemenmaa</u><sup>1</sup>, Mervyn Jones<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Helsinki Metropolia University of Applied Sciences, Helsinki, Finland,<sup> 2</sup>Imperial College London, London, UK</em></p><p>Who should pay for university tuition? What is the effect of tuition fees on the attractiveness and effectiveness of engineering education? What is the role of fees in the financing of university? How do fees match with the principles of equal opportunities?  There are very different practices in collecting tuition fees in different countries in Europe, and even more in the world. Perhaps one extent is Finland, where all the tuition leading to degree is free to all the student and does not depended of their origin. At the other might be the UK where a European student is responsible for paying annual tuition fees of 6k-9k GBP and overseas student a significantly higher rate. In US, Asian and Australian institutions a wide range of fees exists. From a student's viewpoint the total financial load is also depended on the support systems - grants, vouchers, loans and taxation. From university view tuition fees are part of the total financing. In this paper the practices in different countries are discussed. We will focus on items such as, how the fees influence the motivation of studies, how that affects the study possibilities for European student - and for student from further away and finally how fees might affect the quality of teaching and learning. What does this do for the internationalisation of university? Are student selected by talent, money or nationality? An insight comes from a study of Finland with the United Kingdom and a global comparison.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0047</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>The Improvement of Engineering Education Quality Assurance in China</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Quality Assurance and Accreditation</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Yangqiong Qiu</u>, Hanbing Kong <em>Zhejiang University, Zhejiang Province, China</em></p><p>China is cultivating most engineers around the world, almost 90% of Chinese university have established engineering programme. The concern of engineering education quality assurance is becoming the second main factor along with government policy in this  flatten world . Recently China has obtained provisional status of Washington Accord, which encourages the development of the accreditation system in engineering education in China. Chinese government strongly encourages the cooperation between university and industries, both in the cultivation of engineers and the education quality assurance practice. Chinese Education Ministry has launched the Excellent Engineers Training Programs with other departments of the government and engineering societies since 2010. This program sets different categories and multi-scale criteria to prepare engineering talents. This paper discusses the progress in engineering education accreditation system in China, and then explores engineering qualification system from UK, continental Europe and US, concluded with some suggestion about further improvement about quality assurance of engineering education in China.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0048</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Learning Spatial Visualization: Beyond Drills and into Early Mastery</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Emily Farrar</u>, Olufunmilayo Adebayo, Rick Evans, Traci Nathans-Kelly, Tyi McCray <em>Cornell University, Ithaca, NY, USA</em></p><p>student entering university-level engineering programs must be adept at spatial-visualization and reasoning. To raise the performance of first-year student and , the Cornell University Engineering Success (CUES) program used the NSF ENGAGE curriculum to introduce spatial visualization basics. The result were strong, with an overall 13% improvement in tested skills. However, our aims were more ambitious.</p><p></p><p>Our teaching team believed that skills application in authentic spatial-visualization projects would provide deeper learning, applicable toward school and engineering work. Student teams worked with biomedical researchers who asked for professional-level visualizations. We employed an action-research methodology (observations, journals, expert responses, and e-portfolios), tracking their acquisition of spatial concepts, representations, and critical stances. student evidenced knowledge through their innovative use of support tools and technology to create insightful visualizations of complex engineering data and reliably model biomedical mechanisms relevant to human disease. They also demonstrated critical stances by utilizing appropriate, specific and relevant spatial visualization skills to most effectively communicate each engineering concept. Through peer evaluations, student were also able to identify and critique the use of specific spatial skills by other student teams during project presentations.</p><p></p><p></p><p>We will discuss our result which were documented through both qualitative and quantitative methods. Finally, we plan to bring suggestions as to how this approach could transform current  drill and demonstrate  approach, serving as a model for the enhancement of similar courses at other institutions. Our hope was to give student a competitive edge, taking advanced visualization techniques and professional skills into their future projects.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0049</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Articulation and progression: an investigation into the transition of engineering student from applied to more theoretical programme</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Continuing Engineering Education and Lifelong learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal">Marisa Llorens<sup>1</sup>, Susan O'Shaughnessy<sup>1</sup>, <u>Domhnall Sheridan</u><sup>1</sup>, Michael Carr<sup>1</sup>, Sheryl Sorby<sup>2
                    ,1</sup>, Brian Bowe<sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Dublin Institute of Technology, Dublin, Ireland,<sup> 2</sup>Ohio State University, Ohio, USA</em></p><p></p><p>The term  articulation' in higher education refers to student' transition from short cycle applied programme to longer cycle theoretical programme. In many countries (e.g. Scotland, USA) this transition involves transferring from one institution to another (i.e. from college to university). In the Dublin Institute of Technology (DIT), however, this articulation takes place within the institution itself, so that student who successfully complete a 3-year engineering technology programme, known as an Ordinary degree, may apply to progress to the third year of a 4-year Honours degree in engineering, thus earning the Honours degree in five years instead of four. A significant number of the student who receive the Honours degree each year begin their studies in the Ordinary degree programme but the transition between the two programme, and the corresponding shift between applied and theoretical work, especially in mathematics, is not always easy to achieve. While most retention studies at the institution have focused on student making the transition from secondary to higher education in their first year, very little work has been done in examining retention trends for the student who progress from Ordinary to Honours programme. This paper will examine data and student experiences from the past several years to determine factors contributing to retention and eventual graduation for the student who attempt to complete the Honours programme but who started out in the Ordinary programme. Parallels will be drawn to international studies on student articulation, including the transitions involved in the Bologna process.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0050</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Between humanism and competitiveness - towards an <i>intercultural ethos for engineers</i></strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Global Engineer</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Christophe Morace</u><sup>1</sup>, Alison Gourv?Hayward<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Ensta-Bretagne CRF 1410, Brest, France,<sup> 2</sup>Telecom-Bretagne, Brest, France</em></p><p>Ever-increasing globalisation in a complex, competitive and highly technical world has raised the question of ethics and social responsibility for many companies, organisations and individuals. The impact of such socio-technical issues on both engineering practices and education places the question of intercultural competences at the core of this debate. Definitions of intercultural competences deriving from research in the Humanities and Social Sciences tend to focus on an idealised view of humanity, whereas Cultural Intelligence research emphasizes cultural fact-finding and competence development for commercial ends.</p><p>Our research, based on findings from engineers in an intercultural professional context and student in two French Graduate Engineering Schools with an international campus, shows a need for both humanism and competitiveness. Observations of student learning in experiential, intercultural spaces revealed more humanistic attitudes and communication skills, while interviews with professional engineers in a competitive context showed that the greatest commercial success was invariably accompanied by strong humanistic competences.</p><p>In this paper, we will analyse the result of 10 years' practice and research on the transformation of international experience into intercultural competences and suggest a framework, combining humanism and competitiveness, which we call <i>intercultural ethos for</i> <i>engineers</i>. This concept includes cultural and intercultural competences, values and ethics but also self presentation, representation and negotiation of identity which can be observed and analysed in the discourse of practicing and student engineers. Our aim is to provide a contribution to the development of pertinent intercultural competences for the global engineering community.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0052</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Using active learning methods to teach Applied Natural Sciences to first year student</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Sonia M. Gomez Puente</u>, Richard Engeln <em>Eindhoven University of Technology, Eindhoven, The Netherlands</em></p><p></p><p>Teaching <i>Applied Natural Sciences</i> (ANS) would not have ever been so challenging as this subject was not the common course for up to 1,800 first year student at the Eindhoven University of Technology (TU/e). Responding to the educational policy demands from the university educational management, innovation of education was to serve the new profile of the  Engineer<i>S</i> of the Future' by emphasizing diversity in the study programs and by attracting student with different interests, among others. In addition, the curriculum transformation was aiming at increasing student' pass rate. Within this framework, the ANS course has been redesigned to meet curriculum requirements. The didactic underpinnings of the ANS course lie in the combination of active learning techniques, i.e. Peer Instruction method; in the use of ICT, i.e. electronic response devices; and in the integration of formative assessment through electronic platforms.</p><p>The ANS course aims at teaching basic concepts on mechanics, fluid dynamics, harmonic motion, and thermodynamics with the application of active learning approach, to involve actively student during weekly lectures and tutorials.</p><p>In this paper, we report on the result of student' perceptions regarding three consecutive academic years. result show that student became more enthusiastic about the interactive setup of the lectures while pass rates do not show a clear trend. We explore, therefore, how active learning in combination with other methods has supported student to learn physics concepts. For the purpose of this paper we focus on the result of only one group combining physics, chemistry, and mathematics student.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0053</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Diagnostic tests for student bridging to the Master's programmeinEngineering Technology.</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Greet Langie</u>, Carolien Van Soom <em>KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium</em></p><p>In Belgium one distinguishes two types of bachelor degrees: the professional and the academic bachelor. A professional bachelor degree does not grant automatic access to a master's programme, whereas an academic bachelor degree does.However professional bachelors are not excluded from a master's programme, they can start this study after finishing successfully a bridging programme (45-90 ECTS points).</p><p>The number of bridging student in the Faculty of Engineering Technology of KU Leuven is increasing systematically year after year with 7% on average. For the moment 900 student are bridging, whereas 3700 student are enrolled in the academic Bachelor of Science in Engineering Technology. So one out of five student who is trying to get the necessary degree to start a Master's programme in Engineering Technology, is a bridging student.</p><p>The success rate of these bridging programme is however very low. Since these bridging student have already a degree which is very valuable in industry, we would like to give these student a reliable idea of their changes to succeed in a bridging programme before they start these two extra years. In this project we implemented three diagnostic tests, developed for freshman who start the academic Bachelor of Science in Engineering technology (mathematics, academic language skills and scientific reasoning). We have investigated the validity of the tests for this population and we can conclude that only the mathematics test has moderate predictability. </p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0054</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Safety knowledge for professional engineers and student:A global scheme of education.</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Continuing Engineering Education and Lifelong learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Poster</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Eva Giagloglou</u>, Marko Djapan, Christos Tsiafis, Pavle Mijovic, Ivan Macuzic <em>University of Kragujevac, Kragujevac, Serbia</em></p><p>The modern industry continuously adopts new technology and new occupational standards. These novelties bring the need of improved and up to date occupational safety knowledge and practice. In order to offer a complete scheme of education the university of Kragujevac installed three lines of balanced educational packages.</p><p>The first line regards academia, where there are established safety curricula in under and post graduate education as well as various doctorate safety-research programme. In parallel, there is a second line of education, revolted to professionals, under the framework of Lifelong learning. These programme are divided into modules for facilitating the stakeholders' choice. The third line is revolted to research, for providing solutions in main machinery and safety-related problems, in view of continuous and dynamic collaboration with industrial partners.</p><p>Occupational safety is a worldwide basic need, furthermore, legislative and social changes push into a more demanding strategy. These three lines of education are structured to cover the whole spectrum of safety education. The University of Kragujevac assumed the role to up to date the safety professionals, establish collaborations with industry, dynamically get involved into real industrial problems and finally prepare future professionals, able to affront coming challenges in safety issues. This paper presents strategic educational methods and provides qualitative and quantitative result, that may be used by other institutions wishing to implement educational packages of occupational safety. The result include rating of the presented Lifelong learning programme and percentages of hired student, after the completion of their internship in the industrial company.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0055</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Investigating the perceptions of professional engineers that undergraduate engineering student hold?</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Attractiveness of Engineering</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Jenna Tudor</u><sup>1</sup>, Helen Hooper<sup>1</sup>, Oana Bretcanu<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Northumbria University, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK,<sup> 2</sup>Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK</em></p><p>There is an international deficit of scientists and engineers. For example, a 2012 report indicates that training at current rates will result in a 1,000,000 shortfall to meet workforce demands across the next decade just in the US. Such reports call for increased training but also highlight an imperative to develop better retention strategies, especially for women, who are starkly under-represent within many science and engineering fields.</p><p>In order to enhance induction/ transition support for first year student and develop better career/ post graduate study development support we investigated what student understood of the routine activities that professional scientists/ engineers engage with. student at 3 regional HEIs on a range of STEM programme at levels 4 and 6 were challenged to articulate their understanding, along with providing information about pre entry motivations for choice of subject/ university course, post graduate study/ career aspirations and parental/ carer occupation. student were also asked to complete a  Draw a Scientist/ Engineer' task and the visual images drawn were analysed for gender and level of stereotype.</p><p>The data reveals a range of misconceptions, including gender biased stereotypes, variations within data from different HEI's and implications for practice which will be discussed.</p><p></p><p></p><p></p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0057</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Degrading of PhD s through the introduction of doctoral schools</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Erik de Graaff</u> <em>Aalborg University, Aalborg, Denmark</em></p><p>In 2007 SEFI published a statement regarding the third cycle of the Bologna Process: the Doctorate in Engineering. The statement emphasised the importance of individual research work. A PhD in Engineering should reflect the individual s research competencies. Consequently, qualifying as a researcher with a PhD should be the result of an individual learning process rather than curriculum-based education.</p><p>As the third cycle of qualification in higher education is taking shape, many university in different countries established a doctoral school to organise the PhD process. More and more, the doctoral degree program takes the form of a formal curriculum. At least part of the PhD requirements is defined by participation in a course programme.</p><p>Traditionally, PhD theses are the result of university based research projects, or research work performed at research institutes. The task of the supervisor was mostly that of a referee judging when the PhD candidate was ready to defend the thesis, a process that could take up to ten years. Presently a supervisor is expected to coach the PhD student aiming for a degree within four, or even three years.</p><p></p><p>It will be difficult to prove actual degrading of the level of PhD thesis over the past decade. In fact many highly interesting and sophisticated studies are currently being published. However, the fact that people starting their PhD enrol in a three-year doctoral school programme restricts their expectations of developing into a fully independent researcher. The presentation aims to discuss the impact on the careers of young researchers.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0058</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Who Has Heard About the HEAR? Evaluation of initial employer impact of the Higher Education Achievement Record</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Entrepreneurship of Employability</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Jenna Tudor</u>, Roger Penlington, Helen Hooper, Helen Manns <em>Northumbria University, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK</em></p><p></p><p>The Higher Education Achievement Report (HEAR) arose as a recommendation from the final Burgess report  Beyond the Honours Degree Classification' and was first implemented in 2012-2013, with wide spread roll out continuing across the UK HEI sector. The HEAR includes a range of University validated activities - with an underpinning focus on employability, therefore the main risk to the Department/ HEI if the HEAR is not effectively implemented is an impact on the employability of their student. There is currently little information available from employers regarding whether they are aware of the HEAR, what they think of HEARs, if they have seen them, or what they would like to see on a HEAR <i>etc</i>.</p><p>In order to evaluate the initial employer impact of the HEAR we developed a focussed online survey which was administered to over 150 STEM employers and post graduate course admissions tutors and targeted at individuals who participate in the graduate recruitment procedures for the company/organisation. Data was also collected from undergraduate Engineering student to demonstrate the level of student awareness of the HEAR. The session will focus on the data obtained from the Engineering employers and the student to inform future development of the HEAR, to encourage student to engage with relevant HEAR activities and to encourage staff to provide support/opportunities for student to engage with relevant HEAR activities.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0059</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Exploiting the Thesis Research: Educating Engineering PhD student to Think and to Act Entrepreneurially</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Entrepreneurship of Employability</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Aonghus McNabola</u>, Paul Coughlan <em>Trinity College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland</em></p><p>In preparing their thesis, doctoral researchers are challenged to address significant issues with the potential to contribute to knowledge. Increasingly, there is an expectation of relevance to society. For the doctoral researcher, the resulting thesis may form the basis for an innovative and entrepreneurial response to the issue. To realise this potential, doctoral education needs to enable collaboration with other disciplines and with practitioners, and encourage thinking and acting innovatively and entrepreneurially.</p><p>The Graduate Certificate in Innovation and Entrepreneurship is offered to all doctoral student, including Engineering, at Trinity College Dublin as part of a structured PhD Programme. The course locates entrepreneurship and creative thinking in the context of the thesis and challenges student to explore and exploit innovative opportunities for commercial and/or social benefit in the thesis. This course is transforming the doctoral education experience of student by establishing innovation alongside research and education as an integral element of their PhD. The output is a new breed of graduate, expert in their discipline, but confident in innovation and entrepreneurship.</p><p>This paper outlines a longitudinal case study of 6 Engineering PhD student who have engaged in this programme, and is based on student interviews and programme documentation. The integration with the Engineering curriculum is outlined, including, student progression and supervision. The paper reflects on the benefits in terms of graduate attributes and employability.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0061</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Accreditation criteria as enablers</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Quality Assurance and Accreditation</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Deborah Seddon</u> <em>Engineering Council, London, UK</em></p><p>In the UK, the standards of competence and commitment that must be demonstrated to achieve professional registration as an engineers or technician are established by the regulatory body, the Engineering Council. A key element is the required underpinning knowledge and understanding, which for professional engineers is usually delivered via a university degree programme designed to meet the Engineering Council's criteria.</p><p>This paper draws on the Engineering Council's recent five year review of the degree accreditation criteria. This involved collaboration across the profession, including employers, academics and professional organisations, thus providing an opportunity to ensure that engineering degrees continue to equip graduates for employment in the 21<sup>st</sup> century. This paper outlines: the review process; the thinking behind some of the revisions: the balance between avoiding whole-scale change to a standard that was broadly supported by stakeholders, whilst addressing matters that have come to the fore since the previous review (including ethics, security and risk management); and taking account of external drivers from the UK Government and others to enhance skills and graduate employability.</p><p>Particular attention is paid to two key revisions: the integration of what are commonly termed  general learning outcomes' (which tend to underpin the employability or transferable skills that employers say theyrequire) to be within the specific engineering/technical learning outcomes; and the clearer presentation of the distinctiveness between the four types of UK engineering degree. Relevant and appropriate accreditation criteria are presented as enablers for university engineering departments wishing to develop or update their degree programme.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0062</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>The SUTD-MIT Global Leadership Programme: Attempting institutional transplantation through cross-cultural student leadership development</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Global Engineer</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Dara Fisher</u><sup>1</sup>, Aikaterini Bagiati<sup>2</sup>, John Brisson<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, USA,<sup> 2</sup>Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA, USA</em></p><p>Over the last decade, numerous higher education institutions have begun to engage in cross-border efforts and initiatives, especially in the discipline of engineering and technical education. While these efforts have great diversity in size and scope, the largest of these projects are those attempting complete <i>institutional transplantation</i> of the academic, student, and research culture of one institution to another. In 2010, the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) began one such project in collaboration with the Singapore Ministry of Education to create the Singapore University of Technology and Design (SUTD). In planning for this project, the MIT-SUTD Collaboration staff identified three unique pathways towards institutional transplantation: faculty development, undergraduate curriculum design, and initiatives related to student life.</p><p>In the realm of student leadership, MIT staff members sought to transfuse the innovative, entrepreneurial, bottom-up and free-spirited culture of the MIT undergraduate community to the student body of SUTD. To address this goal, in 2013 the Collaboration staff developed and executed the SUTD-MIT Global Leadership Programme (GLP), a ten-week summer exchange in Cambridge, Massachusetts, for 28 members of the inaugural SUTD student cohort. Through GLP, SUTD student actively engaged with the MIT community, while simultaneously receiving training in teamwork, design, entrepreneurship, education, and technical communication, all delivered through the leadership lens and with particular emphasis on the leadership component. This paper presents the design, development, and execution of the inaugural GLP program, as well as an explanation of this program as a specific vehicle for MIT s institutional transplantation effort in the SUTD project.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0063</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Design of an MSc Degree course in Aerospace Structures and Materials</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Gillian Saunders-Smits</u> <em>Delft University of Technology, Delft, The Netherlands</em></p><p>With the implementation of the Bologna Agreement at Delft University of Technology the traditional 5-year Master of Science in Aerospace Engineering degree was split in 3- year BSc degree followed by a 2-year MSc degree. Although initially the actual underlying curriculum was left unchanged the department of Aerospace Structures and Materials decided to redesign their MSc programme to meet the needs of the modern student and facilitate the thought behind the Bologna agreement of student mobility throughout Europe and beyond. The programme will also incorporate online learning and will go live in September 2014.</p><p></p><p>This paper will detail the curriculum design of the new MSc programme, the didactical background on which it is based and share experiences from the lecturers involved in the design process. The paper will be of interest to anyone who is rethinking the design of their existing degree courses.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0064</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Spatial Skills as a Key to Success in Engineering</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Issues of Gender and Diversity</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Sheryl Sorby</u>, Edmund Nevin, Avril Behan, Eileen Mageean, Sarah Sheridan <em>Dublin Institute of Technology, Dublin, Ireland</em></p><p></p><p>Through numerous research studies conducted over the past fifty years, the importance of well-developed 3-D spatial skills for success in engineering and other STEM fields has been widely demonstrated. Research conducted in the U.S. and elsewhere, has demonstrated the high level of spatial skills found in student of engineering and architecture; however, not all of our first-year student have strong spatial skills when they start their post-secondary studies. Poor spatial skills put these student at a distinct disadvantage when completing introductory courses in CAD, descriptive geometry, and graphic communications requirements in many STEM programs. In turn, this often leads to poor grades and dropping out of engineering or architecture as a result. In this study, the spatial skills of first-year student in several engineering and technology programs were assessed through use of standardized instruments. The spatial skills of architecture and computer science student were also assessed. End-of-semester grades for the student in several key courses were also obtained to determine if there is a correlation between spatial skill level and student performance. This paper outlines the result obtained from this study and draws conclusions regarding the importance of spatial skills for success in introductory STEM courses. result obtained through this testing will be compared across disciplines and programs and will be compared to similar data obtained from testing engineering student in the U.S.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0065</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>International Student Teams Solving Real Problems for Industry in Senior Capstone Projects</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Global Engineer</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Either</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Phillip Sanger</u> <em>Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN, USA</em></p><p></p><p>Most undergraduate student do not have the opportunity to travel abroad and experience and develop communication skills with others cultures. However in this global world, today's engineers is likely to have to work in global international teams with colleagues from other nationalities. The challenge for many engineering curricula is how to include, in a realistic way, this global dimension.</p><p>In the Purdue University engineering technology program an international capstone project is being created and introduced in the coming year. This international capstone project builds on the existing, industry sponsored, multi-disciplinary capstone team project that is required of all student. In the international project, half of the team members are student from a non-US university. The full team works on a project proposed by companies with a global footprint in both the U.S. and in proximity to the foreign institution. Most of the global project is carried out using the full range of electronic communication tools such as email, skype, and blogs. In addition two exchange trips are made with team members travelling to their opposite foreign location. Ideally the first trip occurs near the initiation of the project for planning, organizing and conceptualization. One of the challenges is the synchronization of the two curricula and the academic schedules of the two institutions.</p><p>This program is just being launched and this paper will be a progress report for the two first projects being undertaken this fall to increase the global awareness of our student.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0066</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Understanding social learning behaviours of xMOOC completers</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Technology in Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal">Sasha Skrypnyk<sup>2</sup>, Thieme Hennis<sup>1</sup>, <u>Pieter de Vries</u><sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Delft University of Technology, Delft, The Netherlands,<sup> 2</sup>University of South Australia, Adelaide, Australia</em></p><p>In general MOOCs differ from traditional university online courses in two ways: Open access, anyone can participate for free, and Scalability, courses are designed for a large number of participants. In that sense MOOCs are multicultural learning environments that need a sensitive approach in course design and facilitation to deal with the diversity of its student population to enhance participation and completion. Most research focuses on the individual although the opportunities for collaboration are numerous and we know that interaction has a positive influence on learning achievements, but how can this be supported in MOOCs to promote effective learning? Some learners have greater needs collaborating, while others may experience no such needs. Understanding these preferences through learners  behaviours is critical. Identifying what learners are prone to explore the potential of collaboration, and which are not, has implications for pedagogical choices to support diverse learners.</p><p>This paper discusses social learning behaviour of participants in two xMOOCs from the Delft University of Technology (TUD) on the edX platform (Solar Energy and Water Treatment, Fall 2013). The paper will supply an overview of the research findings, describe the type of learners who were socially active and completed the MOOCs and the challenge of making MOOC facilitation and delivery more culturally sensitive. Our research suggest that social interaction with other learners is beneficial for student performance, but that forum strategies and platform affordances create unequal opportunities for participation, as MOOC learners are diverse and their needs differ, in the same way as their backgrounds.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0067</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>To Stay or Leave? A Plan for Using Phenomenology to ExploreGender and the Role of Experiential Learning in Engineering  </strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Education al Research Methods</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Shannon Chance</u><sup>1
                    ,2</sup>, Brian Bowe<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Hampton University, Hampton, VA, USA,<sup> 2</sup>Dublin Institute of Technology, Dublin, Ireland</em></p><p>Today, there is a gap in understanding of <i>why</i> women chose engineering and <i>how</i> they experience collaborative Problem-Based Learning (PBL). Phenomenology provides an ideal framework for studying such a topic.</p><p>This paper presentation discusses the design of a project funded as part of a Marie Curie International Incoming Fellows (IIF) grant to the Dublin Institute of Technology. At the core of the IIF project is a <i>Phenomenological Study of How Women Experience Engineering Education: Understanding How PBL Influences Their Decisions to Join or Leave Engineering</i>. Participants in the study are women in Ireland, Portugal, and Poland from four different segments of the engineering pipeline (high school, college, early career, and late career/CEOs). The sample of 24 includes women who have experienced PBL and others who have not.</p><p>The overall project addresses leaks in Europe's STEM pipeline<strong> </strong>that lead to shortfall and lack of diversity among European engineers. The EU faces an alarming deficit of engineers. In 2009, Belgium had 2500 unfilled engineering positions. In 2011, Germany needed 76,400 more people with engineering skills and 114,000 people with STEM skills. To address this and diversify perspectives, the EU must attract and retain more women in STEM. Prior research suggests that PBL increases student engagement and many help address reasons women avoid STEM subjects.</p><p></p><p>The intent of the SEFI presentation is to promote use of phenomenology in research on engineering education and to help perfect the design of the study through group discussion and critique.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0068</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>An aligned 'design approach' for the engineering curriculum</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Margriet de Jong</u>, Elsje Londers, Inge Van Hemelrijck, Ludo Froyen <em>KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium</em></p><p>student at the Faculty of Engineering Science at KU Leuven develop their engineering design skills in several integrating team assignments 'Problem Solving and Design' (PandD) throughout the curriculum. These assignments gradually increase in complexity and student are increasingly expected to work independently.</p><p>result from a student survey show that student are positive about the PandD concept in general. Yet, student indicate that they receive little or no feedback on their performance in 'design'.</p><p>We aim to improve the assessment of and feedback on design skills by introducing a <i>design approach model</i>, tailored to our educational needs. This model serves as an outline for an aligned design curriculum pathway for a gradual development of student's competence in engineering design.</p><p>The design approach model is a schematic representation of the steps in the engineering design process and includes additional professional skills, such as teamwork, reporting and project management. Already in the first semester assignment the basic model is presented to the student, but we focus on only a few aspects, like teamwork. Subsequent assignments focus on other aspects, e.g. methods for evaluating ideas. At the start of each assignment the model is presented to the student, with an overview of what they learned already and what the focus of the new assignment will be. This will give student insight in how they gradually build up their competence in engineering design. An online system is introduced to guide the student in their self-assessment of the design competencies and to enhance providing structured feedback.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0069</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Analysis of Analytics - Videoclip Watching activities in Introductory Physics</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Physics in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Juho Tiili</u>, Sami Suhonen <em>Tampere University of Applied Sciences, Tampere, Finland</em></p><p>The new studying method, "Combining good practices" , presented in SEFI2013, has been implemented in introductory physics teaching in Tampere UAS. In order to use lectures for active engagement of student and for continuous assessment, the routine-like tasks are pushed in to e-learning environment. Video-solutions, presented via YouTube, for exercise problems present key role in web content. student' studying habits concerning video material is analyzed using data gathered from student, Google analytics and e-learning log files. The data is gathered from the introductory engineering mechanics course. The interesting questions are: 1. How does the video watching activities vary according to the course timeline? 2. How much the videos are watched? 3. How does student' final grade correspond to video watching activities? 4. How do the student use the videos as learning tools? The result of the study show that nearly all of the student have used video material during the course and nearly all of them find it helpful concerning their course performance. It is obvious that activities concerning the video material is concentrated close to the week exams and the final exam. First glance of the statistics show that some of the videos are much more popular than the others. For example the ratio of views/student of the videos can vary from 0,30 to 1,1 within the mechanics course, based on the e-learning environment logs. Based on the log files, almost all student watch the videos, but a slight majority is student with lower final grades.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0070</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Combining good practices in fully online learning environment   introductory physics course</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Sami Suhonen</u>, Juho Tiili <em>Tampere University of Applied Sciences, Tampere, Finland</em></p><p>Based on a selection of good educational practices reported in the literature, a new method to study introductory engineering physics at Tampere UAS was introduced in SEFI 2013 conference. The method relies on:  1. Active engagement 2. Peer instruction 3. Interactive lecture demonstrations 4. Pre-lecture assignments, 5. Small scale measurement tasks 6. Video-content 7. Continuous assessment.  The aim is to implement above mentioned practices in e-learning environment successfully. The challenges are: How to achieve interactivities while presenting demonstrations on video? How to carry out measurements individually at home, but still work on the assignment as a team? And all this with only the equipment a normal student has easily available.  To achieve some interactivities of the demonstrations they are presented in several video episodes, so that the first part only presents the case in question. The student are then asked to record their individual and group discussion based predictions. Only after this the demonstration continues to next episodes and the student can analyze and reflect their conceptions and misconceptions about the phenomenon.  The measurement assignments are divided to smaller tasks. After carrying out individual measurements, the result are shared among the student team. The final result of a measurement assignment is then based on the result of all individual tasks. Assessment will be based both on the individual parts as well as the final result. To keep track on the student' working, the teams are asked to provide a log of their discussions and chat.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0071</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Industrial adjunct professors as a potential resource for developing engineering curricula - apilot study</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Industry involvement in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Per Fagrell</u><sup>1
                    ,2</sup>, Lars Geschwind<sup>1</sup>, Anders J??sten<sup>1
                    ,3</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>KTH, Stockholm, Sweden,<sup> 2</sup>Teknikf??agen, Stockholm, Sweden,<sup> 3</sup>KK-stiftelsen, Stockholm, Sweden</em></p><p>During the last years many university seem to have recognised mobility of personnel as a way to increase knowledge transfer between academia and the surrounding society. Mobility in terms of adjunct faculty from industry is often used by higher education institutions (HEIs) as a means to strengthen the research and the research education. More seldom are adjunct faculty members used in the development of the curricula of bachelor and master level educations, even if companies collaborating with university often say that one of the top reasons to collaborate is the connection with the education and with the competence of the future.</p><p>This paper presents the findings from a pilot study with the aim to investigate if adjunct professors can be used as a strategic resource when it comes to develop engineering curricula. The paper also investigates their balance of work and their preferences and possible intentions to change the balance to more education, i.e. development of engineering curricula, at bachelor and master level. Data from three interviews have been used in the pilot study with the main purpose to form a model for the analysis of ca 30 interviews made during winter and spring 2014 at two university in Sweden. The preliminary result show that both industry and adjunct professors have an interest in education at bachelor and master levels. The bottleneck is, as always, lack of time as the adjunct professors normally only spend one day a week at the university.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0072</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>From a first cycle PBL environment to a more traditional master s programme: student  impressions</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Education al Research Methods</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Jos?anuel Nunes de Oliveira</u><sup>1
                    ,2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Escola Superior de Tecnologia e Gest?de ueda, Universidade de Aveiro, Aveiro, Portugal,<sup> 2</sup>Centro de Investiga? em Did?ica e Forma? de Formadores, Universidade de Aveiro, Aveiro, Portugal</em></p><p>Technology programme at ueda s Polytechnic School (ESTGA), University of Aveiro (UA), have been organised in a PBL environment since 2001. On reflection, it is possible to state that an institutional cultural change has effectively taken place.</p><p>Although ESTGA is one of UA s departments, it is located in an industrialized region, 25km away from Aveiro. Therefore, ESTGA developed its own dynamics: its own campus; its polytechnic nature, and an established PBL environment.</p><p>After Bologna, UA created  continuity master programme , allowing 1<sup>st</sup> cycle graduates to enrol in pre-defined 2<sup>nd</sup> cycle programme without other selection processes. For ESTGA s Electrical Engineering programme, the continuity is the Master in Industrial Automation Engineering (MIAE), offered by the Electronics Engineering and the Mechanical Engineering departments, at UA s main campus. student taking this path face a transition from ESTGA s PBL environment to a more traditional setting.</p><p>This investigation aims to understand the difficulties felt by student in the transition process, and the impact of their PBL background in a more traditional environment. Five out of seventeen student that, over the past years, enrolled the MIASE were interviewed. The interviews were qualitatively analysed.</p><p>result show that student struggle with teacher/student relationships and class organisation in the new environment. student also have initial difficulties with the more formal approach to Mathematics, although they all report that those difficulties fade rapidly. However, student feel better prepared for the practical activities in the master s programme than colleagues with different backgrounds, and proudly report that they feel better equipped to solve problems autonomously.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0073</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Gender and diversity as integral part of engineering education - Review of SEFI conference papers and articles of the European Journal of Engineering Education between 2005 and 2011 for future conclusions</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Issues of Gender and Diversity</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Susanne Ihsen</u>, Katharina Scheibl <em>Technische Universit?M??en, M??en, Germany</em></p><p>Subject of the review are 60 papers and project descriptions that were presented at the SEFI Conferences between 2005 and 2011 and 33 articles that were published in the European Journal of Engineering Education (EJEE) within the same time period, including three special issues Summarizing the total number of 60 papers and 33 articles the topics that are covered can be clustered into four different categories: (1) Gender and diversity relevance in engineering education, (2) cultural change in engineering education and professional practice, (3) women career and leadership, and finally (4) models of work-life-balance.  With a total of 54 papers and articles most contributions fall under the first category. The research orientation varies between project descriptions and empirical research approach. The great majority (60) can be categorized under the dimension Gender Equality on all Levels of Qualification. The papers were published by 225 Authors. While the majority of 152 authors were female, there was also a significant number of 73 male contributors. The authors come from as much as 30 different countries, the majority is originated in European countries.  The paper shows the status of gender and diversity in engineering and will link this to the state of the art of gender and diversity studies. The conclusions discuss further perspectives of the topic in engineering education.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0074</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong> Like Going to Mars , Research Exchange Experience sat Tokyo Institute of Technology</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Global Engineer</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Either</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Jeffrey S. Cross</u>, Kikuo Kishimoto, Hidetoshi Sekiguchi, Masahiro Susa <em>Tokyo Institute of Technology, Meguro-ku, Tokyo, Japan</em></p><p>Since 2005, Tokyo Institute of Technology's (Tokyo Tech) Graduate School of Engineering has created and utilized bilateral summer student research exchanges with premier engineering university world-wide to promote global engineering skills development. Two different research exchange programs were created initially: Summer Exchange Research Program (SERP) with European and American university and then the Asia Oceania Top University League on Engineering (AOTULE) for exchanges with Asian and Oceania university. These formed the basis for a new university-wide program called Tokyo Tech International Research Opportunities Program (TiROP) with many of the same partners. Although these programs require significant financial and human resources to operate, a number of positive attributes have been observed as a result,</p><p>- greater student diversity on Tokyo Tech's campuses and opportunities for overseas and local student to interact</p><p>- student' gain cross-cultural competency, overseas project leadership experience and show foreign language ability improvement</p><p>- increase in univ./school-level exchange agreements and creation of new programs with partners</p><p>- participating student show improved self-confidence and maturity after the exchange is completed</p><p>In other words, overseas research exchanges are well suited for training future global engineers and scientists to work in a non-native language speaking world. In fact, some of the European exchange student have described their living and research experience at Tokyo Tech,"like going to Mars", since it was beyond their imagination. In this presentation, best practices will be discussed on what are the essential elements to maintain sustainable exchanges, program challenges and future prospects.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0075</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Learn different, learn somewhere else. Does changing the environment impact student's leaning?</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Rapha?Bary</u><sup>1</sup>, Michael Rees<sup>2</sup>, Julie Galland<sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>ERPI - University of Lorraine, Nancy, France,<sup> 2</sup>ENSGSI - University of Lorraine, Nancy, France</em></p><p>"<i>It's not what you know that counts anymore. It's what you can learn.</i>" As mentioned by Don Tapscott, the Canadian business strategist, a major issue is to prepare student for an ever-changing future where learning will be fundamental. Therefore, a French engineering school uses self-directed language learning framework to improve both student' proficiency in foreign languages and their capacity to learn autonomously.</p><p>During an eight-hour course the issues and modalities of self-directed learning are presented. But how a traditional class can clarify what self-directed learning is? What can raise student' awareness of the necessity to learn differently?</p><p>Over the time, the course structure and contents has been improved. Yet, we have noticed that student' attention decrease during these long hours in the same classroom even if knowledge transmission and more active phases alternate. As studies suggest that spaces and environments influence teachers' pedagogical practices and student' learning efficiency, we wondered if teaching each sequence in a place, symbolically linked with the content we want to transmit, could impact positively our teaching.</p><p>Consequently, we devised an experiment. Each course sequence takes place in a particular place and, afterwards, student complete a questionnaire in order to evaluate: is changing places meaningful for them? Does it affect their comprehension of what self-directed involves?...</p><p>This paper will discuss the role of the teaching environment and present our self-directed learning framework as well as the course. The result of the questionnaire are presented to testify that student feedbacks validate the experiment and also suggest improvements.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0076</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong><sub> </sub>Team-based learning in Mathematics courses<sub> </sub></strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Maths in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal">Lamjed Bettaieb<sup>1</sup>, <u>Kaouthar Louati</u><sup>1</sup>, Lobna Derbel<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>ESPRIT: Higher institute of ingineering of technology, EL Ghazela, Tunisia,<sup> 2</sup>ISI: High institute of computer sciences, Ariana, Tunisia</em></p><p>Mathematics are essential for the training of an effective engineer, it helps develop skills such as reasoning, rigorousness and responsiveness. On the other hand, its abstractness can somehow demotivate student who deem Mathematics useless in their upcoming professional life. Consequently, adopting a new methodology, which is simple, motivating and interesting has been a significant challenge these past two years at ESPRIT. Besides, while reviewing the form, the content and the objectives of our courses, we have encountered numerous difficulties to apply the active learning pedagogy in basic mathematics courses. In fact, once the engineering speciality subject is selected, a set of interdisciplinary projects meeting corporate expectations are developed using precise mathematical tools. The learners will be extra-motivated because they have to solve factual problems. Our new experience is to combine effective practice and teamwork on so many levels. Team-based learning approach produced spectacular result in terms of learning performance, motivation levels, attendance records as well as engineering skills.</p><p>This paper is to depict our new experience. We relied on statistical and comparative studies between classes, changes in attendance records and examination result. We have also utilized testimonials of student who have tested this new approach.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0077</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Investigating First-Year Engineering student' Understandings of Computer Simulations and Interactivities</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Technology in Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Kelsey Rodgers</u>, Heidi Diefes-Dux, Krishna Madhavan <em>Purdue University, West Lafayette, Indiana, USA</em></p><p><strong>Introduction:</strong> The purpose of this paper is to investigate student' understandings of interactivities, models, and simulations to inform curriculum development. We explore how student assess the level of interactivities of graphical user interfaces (GUIs) that were developed by their peers as part of a nanotechnology simulation design project. Further, we study how student characterize the presence of mathematical models and simulations.</p><p><strong>Context: </strong>In Spring 2014, a cohort of 346 first-year engineering student enrolled at a U.S. Midwestern university were required to develop interactive MATLAB-based GUIs focused on demonstrating foundational nanotechnology concepts through simulations.</p><p><strong>Methodology: </strong>student were asked to determine the level of interactivities and presence of models and simulations in prior student' GUI design projects. student assessed interactivities with a 5-point rubric item. student were also given yes or no questions to assess the presence of a model or simulation. Further, student were asked to explain their ratings. The three GUI projects under review by the student had the following characteristics. (A) Basic Level of Interaction (e.g. clicking to pull up more information, selecting quiz answers), (B) Animation of a Simulation - user can only play the simulation with default input variables, and (C) Simulation - user can change input variables. A mixed-method approach was taken to study student' responses.</p><p>In the full paper, based on identified patterns across the student responses, we discuss implications for future research and curriculum development focusing on simulation design and use.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0078</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Completing the SIP activities framework - what through placement activities should they, and do they, do?</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Industry involvement in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Judith Shawcross</u>, Tom Ridgman <em>University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK</em></p><p>This paper continues work, reported at SEFI 2013, to identify student activities in short industrial placements (SIPs) undertaken during their post graduate degree. The programme studied contains a series of four SIPs where groups of two student work on real issues for the host companies.</p><p></p><p>Exploratory research on preparing graduates for SIPs found a lack of clear and consistent description of the activities. Last year, an activities framework was developed describing a SIP in terms of twelve process activities groups with sixty four associated key activities and five through placement activities groups.</p><p></p><p>This year the aim was to determine the key activities for the five through project activities groups of; project management, managing the relationship with the client, working with others, managing self and working with and managing information, to complete the framework. A review of literature enabled each group to be described in the context of a SIP and broken down into key activities. Following each project, student recorded what they considered to be the most important activities. After sorting and clustering the data, followed by a comparison with the literature, it was possible to determine the key activities.</p><p></p><p>The full result are still being processed but preliminary findings indicate that key activities have been identified for SIP through project activities.</p><p></p><p></p><p>Thus the framework is now complete and this will enable us to describe these complex industrial placements consistently to student, companies and tutors in terms of activities as well as support further research on skill development.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0080</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong><i>PROJECT BASED LEARNING: A CASE STUDY WITH </i><i>INDUSTRIAL ENGINEERING FRESHMEN</i></strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Carolaine Santos</u>, Mayara Bortoti, Marco Pereira <em>USP - School of Engineering of Lorena, Lorena, S?Paulo State, Brazil</em></p><p><i>The various transformations arising from technological, scientific and social advances, among others, have led people to new attitudes and behaviors. The adaptation of individuals, faced with these changes, affects the education. In line with this, university have been investing in new methods of learning in order to prepare the student for their future profession better, because the labor market searches for differentiated professionals who have, besides solid technical training, well-developed soft skills. This paper assesses the development of Industrial Engineering freshmen from the School of Engineering of Lorena, University of S?Paulo, in their first term, making use of Project-Based Learning. student have joined in groups and each group had a tutor. A case study was conducted and the main research tools used were two questionnaires answered by the student, one at midterm and the other at the end, as well as an interview with each of the tutors. In addition, have been also analyzed the material produced by the student throughout the term: reports, minutes of meetings and blogs. It was found that Project-Based Learning: (i)   has accelerated the development of soft skills of student, among which, teamwork, project management and communication stand out and (ii)   has contributed to the improvement of personal and professional development of student more rapidly. An important indirect result was the approval of one of the projects, by funding source, which led the project to be entirely implemented.</i></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0081</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Innovative on Demand International Engineering Programs</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Global Engineer</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Claudio Brito</u><sup>1</sup>, Melany Ciampi<sup>2</sup>, Rosa Vasconcelos<sup>3</sup>, Luis Amaral<sup>4</sup>, Victor Barros<sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Science and Education Research Council - COPEC, S?Paulo, Brazil,<sup> 2</sup>Safety, Health and Environment Research Organization - SHERO, S?Paulo, Brazil,<sup> 3</sup>Pedagogical Council of the School of Engineering - University of Minho, Guimar?, Portugal,<sup> 4</sup>Computer Graphics Center - CCG, Guimar?, Portugal</em></p><p>The world of today is a challenging environment in all aspects including educational. It is a fact that education is important once it provides men the tools that are necessary to act in a world of high technology and real time information availability. It is a scenario that was almost impossible to foresee not along ago. In times of high-speed communication and real time information delivery, information technology in its entire spectrum has become very important for companies and professionals. And it is the science that now provides the environment for new technology application in educational community including. Following these new trends of high education the COPEC International Institute of Education is offering courses in engineering that are customized not only for enterprises but also for groups of professionals or in academia interested in acquiring special knowledge with a valid certification. The programs are dimensioned in according to the knowledge and practice that are necessary for the group of professional engineers or in academia. They make the requirements and the program is designed to fit their needs. They are partially on class and some content on line as long as it comprises the amount of hours that are necessary to accomplish the program focusing in the main goal to have a certified course of specialists in certain field of expertise. The proposed program is an investment that guarantees return by the strategic vision for a successful performance, the higher management capacity and the growth of intellectual capital.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0082</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Focusing the Future of Engineering Education</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Continuing Engineering Education and Lifelong learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Melany Ciampi</u><sup>1</sup>, Claudio Brito<sup>2</sup>, Rosa Vasconcelos<sup>3</sup>, Luis Amaral<sup>4</sup>, Victor Barros<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Safety, Health and Environment Research Organization - SHERO, S?Paulo, Brazil,<sup> 2</sup>Science and Education Research Council - COPEC, S?Paulo, Brazil,<sup> 3</sup>Pedagogical Council of the School of Engineering - University of Minho, Guimar?, Portugal,<sup> 4</sup>Computer Graphics Center - CCG, Guimar?, Portugal</em></p><p>The world that student are facing has some characteristics that have consequences for the formation of engineers. One of them it the constant changes in the way people develop the work. This aspect is enhanced by the quick and strong technology development. student today require more advice than properly information acquisition once information is now available any time any place and in a huge amount and they are connected all time. The definitions of teacher and student are changing and Education is moving out of episodic experiences at traditional institutions like classrooms and schools into learning flows that course through our daily lives. So utilizing emerging technology to provide expanded learning opportunities is critical to the success of future generations. Teachers have to be prepared to motivate and entice the student about getting knowledge pertinent for their formation as engineers. The use of new technology in classroom is also an important requirement for teachers in High Education principally in Engineering, it is part of teaching environment now. It is clear that it is life long learning environment not only for future engineers but also for the teachers. This paper describes the "International Engineering Educator" Program developed by the engineering education research team of COPEC   Science and Education Research Council. It is offered by the International Institute of Education of COPEC an organization that certifies in according to the Ministry of education of the Country in according to the National Law of High Education, with an international certification.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0083</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Future teaching of mathematics for engineers</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Maths in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Frode R??ng</u> <em>Norwegian University of Science and Technology, Trondheim, Norway</em></p><p>In many countries an increased awareness of the quality of learning and teaching mathematics for engineers can be observed, and many projects are being launched aiming at improved learning outcome for student. This paper will report on a project at the Norwegian University of Science and Technology, where basic mathematics is being taught to around 1500 engineering student in each cohort. The project is in its initial phase, building on a pilot project from 2013.</p><p>The overarching aim of this project is that the student should develop a deep understanding for mathematical concepts and processes, making them better equipped to use mathematics in applications. To reach this aim it is recognised that student  own activities and involvement is crucial, and that an increased communication between student and teachers is essential. An important part of the project is using digital technology where this is advantageous in order to free teacher resources for use in  better  ways, i.e. to enhance contact with student. Digital technology is also important to offer diverse learning resources, acknowledging that student work and learn in different ways.</p><p></p><p>From the pilot project there exist empirical data from interviews of a small number of student and answers to a survey that was administered to the whole cohort. The paper will report on the main elements of the project as well as findings from the pilot study. These data indicate that student are rather conservative in their choices. Traditional elements like textbook and lectures are still in very high regard.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0084</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Engineering creativity education in Russian university</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Engineering Design</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Either</p><p class="MsoNormal">Irina Pertova, <u>Viktoriya Zaripova</u> <em>Astrakhan Engineering Institute of Civil Construction, Astrakhan, Russia</em></p><p>During the TEMPUS TUNING-RUSSIA project (2010-2013) 18 Russian university together with European partners interviewed 358 employers, 1788 graduates, 187 professors in order to elaborate and estimate the list of generic competences in nine different subject areas, including ICT. The questionnaires rated the importance of generic and professional competences for professional work, and level of university performance in teaching of each competence.</p><p>It revealed the strengths and weaknesses of the educational program. Graduates estimated competences Ability for abstract thinking, analysis and synthesis? Ability to team-work? Knowledge and understanding of the subject area and profession?as highly important, but having insufficient level of development in Russian university.</p><p>A project-oriented course Methods of Creativity in Engineering?was elaborated to correct this situation. It provides student with a practical introduction to the methods of engineering creativity (brainstorming, Delphi method, morphological analysis and synthesis, Theory of Inventive Problem Solving - TRIZ, etc.). Its second part is devoted to the new group of software products designed to support innovation processes in enterprises - computer Aided Innovation?(CAI).</p><p>The article discussed in details the structure of the course, result of the course mini-projects, and the core of CAI, developed on the basis of energy-information method of conceptual design [1].</p><p>student peer review demonstrates that the competences have a good enough level of implementation in the course program.</p><p>[1] M.Zaripov, I.Petrova, V.Zaripova Use of integrated base of knowledge on physical effects during training the engineers., Proceedings of the 30th SEFI Conference, Firenze 8-11 September 2002, p.102</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0085</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Inter-department Project Based Learning for Doctor's Course student</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Yasuyuki Yokono</u>, Shigehiko Kaneko, Shigeo Maruyama, Mamoru Mitsuishi <em>The University of Tokyo, Tokyo, Japan</em></p><p>Today s doctoral education must prepare student to be able to work in a broader spectrum and apply one s skills to a multidisciplinary setting while maintaining a high level of expertise. In order to solving some of world's complex problems, innovative doctors cultivated with literacy (language, information literacy, technological literacy, legal knowledge, and ethics) and competency (creativity, problem identification and solution, planning and execution, self-management, teamwork, leadership, a sense of responsibility and duty) are highly desired. To obtain these abilities, it is not enough to take a university lecture or to conduct an experiment in a laboratory.</p><p>This paper outlines the development of inter-department Project Based Learning for doctor's course student. In this course, student leaders and members deal industrial world-based themes and make solutions under the guidance of an industrial project manager and additional help from faculty facilitators. The teams are consisted by different specialization and nationality student. The aim of the Project Based Learning is to provide tough training in problem solving based on needs and integrated cooperation with other fields, to become aware of the importance of trans-disciplinary exchange, to experience team management, and to give tough training in communicating result. Instead of student from the same field working toward a specific goal in the fastest possible time, the PBL is characterized by student from different departments working together on an interdisciplinary problem.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0087</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Challenges of teaching and learning in first-year engineering studies - teachers' observations</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Education al Research Methods</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Pirjo Pietik?en</u><sup>1</sup>, P?i Kinnunen<sup>2</sup>, Erkki Pesonen<sup>3</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Aalto University, School of Chemical Technology, Espoo, Finland,<sup> 2</sup>Aalto University, School of Science, Espoo, Finland,<sup> 3</sup>University of Eastern Finland, School of Computing, Joensuu, Finland</em></p><p>In this paper we discuss the observations of our on-going study on engineering teachers' experiences of challenges that teaching first-year student pose to teachers. We have concentrated on subject independent challenges in order to be able to underline questions relevant to a larger audience of first year teachers. In many studies in engineering education field student' point of view is emphasized and teachers' or teaching organizations' viewpoint is not in a focus. Thus, this paper contributes to building a holistic picture of teaching and learning processes at the higher education level by providing less documented point of view.</p><p>As a data we have altogether 15 teacher interviews from two university. Our interviewees included computer science teachers and chemical engineering teachers. Qualitative content analysis revealed several challenges teachers face, such as, teaching problems solving skills, enhancing motivation, finding out the student' knowledge level and understanding the ways student are thinking, and finally also resources that university provides for teaching. The result showed surprisingly similar kinds of challenges regardless of the university or field. The result provide material for discussion on pedagogical leadership as well as relevant information for demands and planning of pedagogical training.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0088</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Global Engineering Skills - Practice and Perspective  of Joint Educational programme in Engineering   between a German and Malaysian university  -</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Global Engineer</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Axel Hunger</u><sup>1</sup>, Marzuki Mustafa<sup>2</sup>, Stefan Werner<sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>University of Duisburg-Essen, Duisburg, Germany,<sup> 2</sup>Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, Bangi, Malaysia</em></p><p></p><p>Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia (UKM, The National University of Malaysia) and University Duisburg-Essen (UDE) in Germany co-operate since 2000. Major result are double degree (Bachelor and PhD) and exchange programme (all levels). Both partners collaborate on  eye level', agree on outcomes of degree courses and carefully check for equivalences in their curricula. Student mobility shows more than 100 persons in each direction. In 2011, UKM received the "Best Jury Award for Higher Education Institute for Providing Global Student Exposure" from World Education Summit, New Delhi, India; collaboration with UDE was highlight for merit of the award.</p><p>Partnership has been institutionalised by the UKM-Mercator Office, an outpost of UDE at UKM, established in 2002, and UKM International Office at UDE, established in 2010, acting as bridge head at the partner.</p><p>Recently, partners are fine-tuning their programme to prepare graduates for the global labour market, beyond pure technical contents, which is standardised around the world. Credits are offered for non-technical courses with intensive experience regarding foreign culture and behaviour as key for global engineering competence.</p><p>Partners shared many best practices and learned the work culture which is crucial to sustain long term collaboration. Next step will be to integrate further partners in Southeast Asia, creating a network including south-south mobility to share work load and give the network more strength and visibility. In this context, curricula will be enhanced by new courses integrating technical subjects and cultural experience (e.g. by capstone projects) to give good grounds for the "Global Engineering Skills" offered.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0089</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Authors' perceptions of peer review of conference papers and how theycharacterise a  good' one</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Education al Research Methods</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Anne Gardner</u>, Keith Willey <em>University of Technology, Sydney, Sydney, Australia</em></p><p></p><p>Peer review has been the focus of study at conferences of the Australasian Association for Engineering Education (AAEE) since 2010. The preliminary studies were extended to explore AAEE authors' perspective/s of the potential of peer review to support their development as researchers. An important objective of this research is to help members of the AAEE community to better understand themselves and their peers as they transition to the different perspectives and research methods involved in educational research compared to most engineering research.</p><p>This paper describes a study which was undertaken with active members of the AAEE community to explore the following questions:</p><ul><li>What is the perceived purpose of peer review?</li><li>What does the community mean by quality in the context of a conference paper?</li><li>What are the characteristics of a quality review on a conference paper?</li></ul><p>Participants came from a range of types of university and with various levels of educational research experience. A thematic analysis of interview transcripts showed that providing feedback to authors in reviews was equally as important to them as the role of quality assurance of the conference papers. We were able to establish for these AAEE authors the characteristics of both a quality conference paper and a quality review. The result of this study are first steps in improving our shared understandings of what constitutes quality research in engineering education and how we might better convey that in offering constructive advice to authors when writing a review of a conference paper.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0091</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Mapping the landscape of engineering education research: an Australian perspective</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Education al Research Methods</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Anne Gardner</u>, Keith Willey <em>University of Technology, Sydney, Sydney, Australia</em></p><p></p><p>Engineering education research is still consolidating as a recognised research area in Australian university. This paper reports using a landscape model to demonstrate engineering education as a knowledge domain that includes a variety of areas of endeavour. This landscape was motivated by questions about how we define our research domain including the perceived differences between practice, scholarship and research and how the engineering education community can better understand and support itself to collectively achieve wider recognition. This paper reports the responses of 19 authors from a range of institutions and experience levels at the 2012 Australasian Association for Engineering Education (AAEE) annual conference to the landscape model.</p><p>The model stimulated dialogue around the nature of topics in our community and allowed participants to find a place to belong in the landscape. We argue that such a dialogue will not only help develop a community identity, important for a knowledge domain that is still emerging in Australian university but also support colleagues and postgraduate student seeking to participate in or move within it. We suggest that an understanding of the landscape could potentially dissipate the ultimately divisive tensions between scholars, practitioners and researchers. We argue that our community should provide an environment aimed at improving the quality of publications and the development of academics wherever they are on the landscape.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0092</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Combining flipped instruction and multiple perspectives to develop cognitive and affective processes</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Keith Willey</u>, Anne Gardner <em>University of Technology, Sydney, Sydney, Australia</em></p><p> </p><p>Flipped instruction is a form of blended learning that replaces transmission-based lectures with more participative, interactive and collaborative learning opportunities. Activities are typically undertaken before, during and after class, freeing in class time for student to engage in dialogue, and include assessment (typically formative) to allow them to evaluate their understanding and progress in meeting the desired learning outcomes. Flipping creates an opportunity for academics to provide more dynamic feedback to student, and to receive feedback from student about both the activities they are undertaking and what they don't yet understand. Hence, the learning environment is socially constructed as academics and student combine to influence the nature, focus, complexity and timing of subject activities. Social cognitive theory provides a way to frame our thinking about this learning context by foregrounding aspects such as the environment created for learning, as well as considering development of student self-efficacy and how to scaffold the processes for this development.</p><p>This paper reports the exploratory phase of an ongoing study investigating relationships between engagement, mastery of the subject concepts, affective outcomes and professional identity development in the context of flipped instruction. The study supported modification of our collaborative learning modelto explicitly provide multiple perspectives to assist student to overcome learning thresholds, develop disciplinary literacy, professional identity and expertise. In addition, it highlighted the impact of scaffolding and learning activities design on affective outcomes such as self-efficacy and includes the need for activities and assessments to be designed to enhance learning visibility. </p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0093</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Impact of threshold exams on student learning</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Quality Assurance and Accreditation</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal">Keith Willey, <u>Anne Gardner</u> <em>University of Technology, Sydney, Sydney, Australia</em></p><p>Despite academic claims that all topics in their subject are requisite, student are often able to pass assessment tasks with unsatisfactory, and perhaps even no capacity to demonstrate learning in some topics. Furthermore, while undertaking an exam can highlight learning deficiencies there is often no assessable opportunity to address these learning gaps. The aim of our study was to investigate the impact of a two-stage examination process on student' motivation and approach to learning and its capacity to provide both assurance and feedback on their learning. The first stage of the process was a multiple-choice exam, with a pass mark of 80%, covering all requisite subject topics. student receive immediate feedback on their strengths and weaknesses when answering questions through the locally designed technology. An exam review was held one week after the threshold exam in which common misconceptions and misunderstandings were explored. This enabled student to review identified areas of weakness before attempting the second stage of the exam. The study demonstrated that a two-stage examination motivated student to learn and provided them with an opportunity to first identify and subsequently address learning gaps. However we found that student need assistance to change both their method and culture of learning with supporting scaffolding to better manage and benefit from the opportunities threshold exams provide.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0094</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Improvement of the Engineering Student s Training inside University Laboratories through Quality Management Systems</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Poster</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Luca Podesta'</u>, Gianluca Sforza <em>University 'La Sapienza', Rome, Italy</em></p><p></p><p></p><p>This article analyzes the potentialities and the various consequences that may occur during engineering student s educational path when they undertake a training activities, both if it is a thesis work or an internship, in a laboratory implementing a Quality Management System (QMS).</p><p>This is important because it may change the job s organization (perspectives) and the problem solving approach, and it gives student a very important added value appreciated in workplaces.</p><p>First the key points of a QMS are analyzed and how these are related to training activities of the student. Even the economic aspects have been considered as a function of the quality objectives to be achieved.</p><p>Some case studies are presented, illustrating a series of processes developed in a laboratory of the Faculty of Civil and Industrial Engineering - University  La Sapienza  that were tested during the academic year.</p><p>Finally, some processes are illustrated in which student were able to complete the task training through internships and thesis following a training set in a context of quality.</p><p></p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0095</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Connecting Higher Education, Business and Research to develop a Future Educational Ecosystem</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Industry involvement in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Ricardo Abdoel</u><sup>1</sup>, Sharda Kawarmala<sup>1</sup>, Ilona Verwaal<sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Fontys School of Engineering, Eindhoven, Noord Brabant, The Netherlands,<sup> 2</sup>Fontys CoE HTSM Objexlab, Eindhoven, Noord Brabant, The Netherlands</em></p><p>The Eindhoven region in the south of the Netherlands is the heart of the high-tech industry. The regional companies have understood that collaboration in manufacturing, development and innovation with suppliers is key to retaining a competitive position in the world. Fontys University is fully aware of the dynamics and significant (economic) potential of the high-tech manufacturing industry. Fontys plays an important role in the regional innovation system as an industry partner and it is leading the way in higher education in advanced emerging manufacturing technology. As such, Fontys has decided to collaborate with regional industry to invest in and develop a new Centre of Expertise focusing on high-tech manufacturing and materials. This new development will boost cooperation and partnerships on many different levels, helping to fulfil our stakeholder's different needs. In general, this model of public-private cooperation will contribute to our government's goals and Brainport's human capital agenda. The demand for more and better engineers is closely connected to curriculum development. Interesting enough due to technological development entrepreneurship plays an important role. This means that the engineers of the future must be equipped with more than just deep technical competences. Non-Technical competences as in communication skills, project management, group dynamics etc. becomes more important. The Eindhoven region is also very attractive for international student and knowledge workers. The cultural aspects should not be underestimated. In this paper we will investigate these different aspects and how to connect higher education to international operating high-tech businesses by collaborating and executing applied research</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0096</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Putting mathematics  into a form that a non-engineers will understand </strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Maths in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Eileen Goold</u> <em>Institute of Technology Tallaght, Dublin, Ireland</em></p><p></p><p>A study of engineers practising in Ireland provides evidence for a requirement to better match the mathematics taught in engineering education with the mathematics required in engineering practice. In particular mathematical thinking has a greater relevance to engineers' work compared to mathematics contained in school and engineering curricula. A significant difference between engineering education and practice, highlighted by the study, is the social aspect of work compared to education. Tackling workplace problems is usually a team effort while in engineering education problem solving is mostly an individual effort. Engineers maintain that engineering education mostly imparts knowledge while the role of practising engineers is "to frame the problem correctly and maybe express it in maths, then they have to solve it and then they have to interpret the solution and communicate that to the decision maker". The study found that graduate engineers' difficulty communicating mathematics is a significant weakness of engineering education and consequently when engineers move from engineering education into engineering practice they do not realise their mathematical ability. The study also found that the ability to communicate mathematics and its relevance is the predominant characteristic of good mathematics teachers.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0097</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>TeachING-LearnING.EU   Three years of improving German engineering education and what can be learned for Europe</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Dominik May</u><sup>1</sup>, Katharina Schuster<sup>3</sup>, A. Erman Tekkaya<sup>2</sup>, Anja Richert<sup>3</sup>, Sabina Jeschke<sup>3</sup>, Marcus Petermann<sup>4</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>ZHB - TU Dortmund University, Dortmund, NRW, Germany,<sup> 2</sup>IUL - TU Dortmund University, Dortmund, NRW, Germany,<sup> 3</sup>IMA/ZLW and IfU - RWTH Aachen University, Aachen, NRW, Germany,<sup> 4</sup>FVT - Ruhr University Bochum, Bochum, NRW, Germany</em></p><p>Some people get allergy-like symptoms as soon as they hear the word  Bologna . Stultifying bureaucracy, unbearable workload, annoying accreditation agencies or failed goals are just some exaggerated associations. But were the last 12 years really completely misled?   TeachING-LearnING.EU  - The Competence and Service Center for Teaching and Learning in Engineering Education  has been seeking to use the reform as a catalyst for innovating German engineering education. Combining research with effective result oriented teacher coaching and strategic instruments for connecting stakeholders was the main approach throughout the years. Now after learning a lot and applying the knowledge, it seems inevitable to reflect on the previous activities and to build a roadmap for applying the findings in a broader context. This paper presents the major project-result by answering these questions:</p><p>(1) What are higher education researchers , teaching staff s, student , and employers  individual perspectives on engineering education and how can they be involved in the improvement of engineering education effectively?</p><p>(2) How can Student centred teaching concepts be integrated effectively and what are challenges that are unique to engineering?</p><p>(3) How can large audience lectures be innovated and which communication technology can help doing so?</p><p>(4) The project has been running for three years - What were the major lessons learned on a meta-level and how can this be used to build a roadmap for upcoming projects and activities?</p><p>Answering these questions this papers deduces recommendations for future engineering education itself and future engineering education research in Europe.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0098</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>ALLES ING! Count me in! Using the Role Model Concept to Attract Pupils and student to Engineering Sciences</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Attractiveness of Engineering</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Poster</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Theresa Janssen</u>, Natascha Strenger, Sulamith Frerich, Marcus Petermann <em>Ruhr Universit? Bochum, NRW, Germany</em></p><p></p><p></p><p>While engineering graduates are highly sought-after in technology driven countries such as Germany, the numbers of freshman student   especially non-traditional-student - in these subjects is still below that of other disciplines. Interpreting these numbers, it is argued that among the reasons for pupils  reluctance to choose engineering sciences are intense curricula and high demands of those subjects. A different but apparently no less important factor in keeping pupils from studying engineering sciences is considered to be their rather low social acceptance and  coolness  factor.</p><p>At the Ruhr-University Bochum, the three engineering faculties (Civil and Environmental Engineering, Electrotechnology and Information Technology and Mechanical Engineering) have joined forces in 2013 and started a common initiative for attracting pupils and student to their study programs: ALLES ING!, an online platform that portraits student and scientific staff alike and introduces female engineers, teams and technical themes. Research topics (for Bachelor, Master, or doctoral theses) are presented by their respective authors and even career perspectives are depicted in videos of alumni at their actual workplace. The initiative is designed not only to attract new student, but also to increase the identification of those who are already studying at Bochum s engineering faculties with their subject. Functioning as role models, the people and topics in engineering sciences are presented   basing on scientific facts, but never forgetting the importance of an attractive and interest-rousing presentation.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0099</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>The Global Engineer: the student' Standpoint</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Global Engineer</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Either</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Abheesha Busawon</u>, Roger Penlington, Noel Perera, Jenna Tudor <em>Northumbria University, Newcastle, UK</em></p><p>The concept of being a global engineers has become the subject of much debate within the engineering education and profession. The engineering sector is faced with new engineering challenges such as the need to address the impact of globalisation and sustainability, skills-gap, and the  greening  of the job market. It is therefore imperative to initiate a re-skilling of the curriculum starting from the student  perspective to restore confidence in engineering.</p><p>This paper describes a project that is currently under way which sought to investigate how engineering undergraduates viewed professional recognition, whether they believe they have gained the important engineering attributes, their assessment of employability through their degree programme including future mobility, and how confident they are to compete within global markets.</p><p>The student acted as primary stakeholders in this project with participants coming from a range of backgrounds from the engineering undergraduate programme including Mechanical Engineering, Electrical Engineering and Computing within the Faculty of Engineering and Environment.</p><p>The survey carried out within the Faculty so far demonstrates that over half of student participants are confident about obtaining a job after graduating with the skills they have acquired. The findings also recognised opportunities to increase confidence in becoming competent global engineers and concept of mobility since only a minority of student have strong intentions of competing on the international job market.</p><p></p><p>The outcomes of this project hope to generate awareness to increase support for student to participate in dialogues surrounding these issues and promote the global engineering education.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0100</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Setting up a New Culture of Teaching and Learning at the Technische Universit?Berlin: The Ziethen-Workshops </strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Ethics and leadership</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Patrick Thurian</u>, Cornelia Raue <em>Technische Universit?Berlin, Berlin, Germany</em></p><p>In 2012 the TU Berlin initiated the program "First class for our student" in order to improve the conditions of studying and teaching. The program supports a better academic staffing for all status groups as well as measures for didactic qualifications and counseling. The program has eight subprojects. The subproject "tu inspire" was designed as a qualification and reputation program for teaching and learning. In order to level higher teaching and learning at TU Berlins agenda, we decided to organize two retreats aiming for creating a guiding coalition. Hence in 2012 and in 2013, vice presidents, deans, deans of studies, awardees for good teaching, administrative staff as well as student and university didactic staff came together in Ziethen nearby Berlin for three days. The retreats were designed as strategic workshops that provided space for the various perspectives of the participants on teaching and learning and created a sense of common goals. First result are the declaration on teaching and learning ("Ziethener Manifest") drafted by the participants and the formation of eight working groups, e.g. "Improving communication within TU Berlin", "Teaching and learning: spreading, piloting and imparting new ways of teaching and learning among university teachers". All working groups are open to all members of TU Berlin to take part in this process of change. Due to this an avalanche effect is observed which seems to bring the university to a new culture of teaching and learning within the next years. result of the workshops and working groups will be presented.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0101</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Enabling backchannel communication between a lecturer and a large class</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Technology in Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Mirjam Sophia Glessmer</u>, Marc-Andr?ick, Patrick G??ch <em>Hamburg University of Technology, Hamburg, Germany</em></p><p>Large classes make communication difficult between student and instructors. In a large lecture theater setting, the lecturer is situated far away from the student, and sitting in rows hinders group discussions and promotes anonymity. In a recent tutorial offered to some hundred student in such a setting, we realized that some of the challenges the student were experiencing and expressing to each other never made it to the instructor s attention and hence were not explicitly addressed.</p><p>To increase the instructor s awareness of the state of the student  understanding and to reduce the threshold of asking questions in front of their peers, a  backchannel  tool was designed: a website where student can anonymously post questions. Those questions appear in real time at a moderator s screen, where they can be deleted or forwarded to the instructor so that the instructor can choose to address them at a suitable time.</p><p>Evaluation of a pilot run showed that student appreciate the opportunity to ask questions anonymously, and that instructors welcome the insights. Additionally, the record of questions helps to understand the student  learning   the data can be used as basis for learning analytics to see how the quality, quantity and type of questionsdevelops over time. We present this to discuss both the advantages and disadvantages of our approach, as well as the usefulness of the data as basis for learning analytics studies.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0102</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Engineering Graduate Employability - an international comparison.</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Global Engineer</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Tom Ridgman</u><sup>1</sup>, Mingzhen Liu<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK,<sup> 2</sup>University of Oxford, Oxford, UK</em></p><p>There has been a long history in the US and UK of criticism of the work readiness of new engineering graduates. The output of the many surveys tends to point to a familiar list of skill shortages, to a level where the surveys have become a self reinforcing piece of folk wisdom with little empirical supporting evidence. The Chinese HE system is rapidly expanding, 6.6 million fresh graduates left university in 2011, but China Post reported that it has never been harder for employers to find appropriate people; indicating that similar criticisms are emerging but not based on a historic perspective. This study was conducted to explore the Chinese industry's expectation for engineering graduates who constitute the largest proportion of graduates in China, but only 10% are considered employable. The findings were compared with UK studies which demonstrated that industry's expectation and also the effectiveness of the HE system are different. The Chinese industry's expectation for engineering graduates differed in a number of aspects such as the importance of working experience, preferred engineering disciplines and expected attributes etc. The comparison also showed that the effectiveness of the higher engineering education in the UK and China are different depending on certain aspects. These differences need to be further understood to determine whether producing Global engineers can be a reality.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0105</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Democratic co-determination and responsibility of lecture content</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Poster</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>S?? Hansen</u>, Jens B. Bennedsen <em>Arhus University, Aarhus, Denmark</em></p><p>One of the most important challenges for us as instructors is to facilitate reflective behavior in our student in an attempt to achieve deep learning. Here follows that we want the student to engross themselves in the course material and to assume responsibility for their own learning. Traditional approach for university teaching is that the instructor presents some topic(s), where small exercises, such as TPS, clickers, minute paper etc. may be inlaid, however it is still the instructor that controls and ensures a strict path is taken. This is often perceived as being served "a meal" by the student.</p><p>A teaching methodology described by Herskin (http://samfundslitteratur.dk/user/9649/public-profile) addresses this challenge. Our design is concretization of this; it is a student centred approach, where it is up to the student to figure out what they want the instructor to talk about based on pre-planned lectures (curriculum, presentation and exercises). To facilitate this, the lecture starts by having the student work in groups of 10-15, where they discuss the combined material for 35-50 minutes. During the following intermission their feedback is used as a base line to create a talk that has emphasis on the parts they so desire.</p><p></p><p>In this paper we</p><ol><li><p>present a didactical design inspired by Herskin</p></li><li><p>evaluate it in terms of the student view on:</p></li></ol><ul><li><p>The perceived load</p></li><li><p>A change in preparation</p></li><li><p>An effect of the redesign</p></li><li><p>An acceptance of the approach</p></li><li><p>Group dynamics</p></li></ul><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0106</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Introducing complexity into project management through multi-stakeholders interactions</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal">Myriam Le Goff-Pronost<sup>1</sup>, <u>Bruno Vinouze</u><sup>1</sup>, Matthieu Arzel<sup>1</sup>, Antoine Beugnard<sup>1</sup>, Jean-Philippe Coupez<sup>1</sup>, Fran?s Gall<sup>1</sup>, Claire Lassudrie<sup>1</sup>, Michel Morvan<sup>1</sup>, Richard Na<sup>2</sup>, Didier Baux<sup>3</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Telecom Bretagne, Brest, France,<sup> 2</sup>Lyc?Vauban, Brest, France,<sup> 3</sup>Didier Baux Communication, Quimper, France</em></p><p>Telecom Bretagne is a French graduate engineering school in Information and Communication Technology. One of our ambitions is to train globally competitive technical managers able to cope with complex projects. To this end, we developed project based learning where student are in a practical situation close to their future career as an engineers. In this paper, we describe the project organisation and focus on the interactions between stakeholders (large student groups, customer, various experts, communications coach and methodology supervisors). student have to perform a techno-economical study with a great freedom as to their team organisation. student must discover the specific role of the stakeholders and must adjust the communication level to each interlocutor. Experts can be requested by the student to help them with technical matters. The methodology supervisors check if student  methods are efficient, they point out dysfunctions and can provoke unexpected events. A communications coach can be requested by student to help in conflict management within the team or with the stakeholders. In order to quantitatively analyse the student  progress in stakeholders  interactions, a self assessment questionnaire was proposed before and after the course. This questionnaire covered interpersonal skills (teamwork, communication) and personal skills (adaptation to change, stress resistance). The student  assessment shows a significant evolution of their management skills and their perception of complexity. Project organisation with many stakeholders and large student groups brings opportunities to illustrate complex situations. In the future, we aim to improve the experiment and analyse feedback aver a longer period.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0107</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Preliminary evaluation of an intervention to increase student success of first year student in engineering education</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Education al Research Methods</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Maartje van den Bogaard</u>, Ellen Sjoer <em>Delft University of Technology, Delft, The Netherlands</em></p><p>This paper reports on part of a qualitative study on student  experiences with and perceptions of their educational environment in their first year in Delft University of Technology. The focus of this study are student  experiences with an intervention designed specifically to increase student success in the first year of enrolment: the Exclusion of Reenrolment Rule. In this study a qualitative approach was used to collect data from a large sample of first year student representing 8 bachelor courses over the course of the first year. Outcomes of the study indicate that the intervention is not successful in the sense that few student feel challenged by it. At the same time the intervention is effective as student who are failing are quick to seek help. This qualitative approach turned out to be of value to learn about effectiveness of intervention such as the exclusion of reenrolment rule early on.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0108</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Black boxes in electronics engineering labs</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Education al Research Methods</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Pieter Coppens</u><sup>1
                    ,2</sup>, Johan Van den Bossche<sup>1
                    ,2</sup>, Mieke De Cock<sup>3
                    ,2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Faculty of Engineering Technology, KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium,<sup> 2</sup>LESEC, KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium,<sup> 3</sup>Department of Physics and Astronomy, KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium</em></p><p>Based on previous research [1-2], we reshaped a 2nd year electronics engineering lab on RC-filters. In the new setting, student have to prepare for the lab session by using a newly developed simulation to train them in oscilloscope reading and construction of a Bode plot. During the lab, a  black box' approach is implemented to force student to think about the measuring procedure and the concepts related to these RC-filters.</p><p>Several groups of student were videotaped to analyse student' performance and activities in the lab.In the paper, we will briefly outline the analysis method of the videotapes, as well as its performance. We will use the result of the video analysis to verify the student' differences in activities in the new laboratory.</p><p>[1]Coppens, P., and De Cock, M. (2013). Exploring student' activities and learning in an analog electronics lab session. In 41th SEFI Annual Conference. Leuven.</p><p>[2]Coppens, P., Cock, M. De, and Kautz, C. (2012). Student Understanding of Filters in Analog Electronics Lab Courses. In 40th SEFI Annual Conference:Engineering Education 2020: Meet the Future. Thessaloniki.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0109</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Bridging the skills gap in STEM industries</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Industry involvement in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Coorous Mohtadi</u><sup>1</sup>, Owen McAree<sup>1</sup>, Joachim Schlosser<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>MathWorks Ltd, Cambridge, UK,<sup> 2</sup>MathWorks Gmbh, Ismaning, Germany</em></p><p>The gap between skills of university graduates in engineering disciplines and expectations of industrial employers poses a number of challenges for both employers and university. Employers find that the new employees far from being able to contribute immediately need to be retrained in areas such as Model-Based Design that is used extensively in industry and not embraced fully in education. A recent survey of employers and academics in the UK performed by YouGov PLC demonstrates:</p><ul><li>Majority believe a gap exists between the skills of graduates and requirements of industry</li><li>To narrow this gap will potentially take a decade and will require collaboration between industry and university in curriculum development</li><li>60% of the respondents believe that project based learning approach can narrow this gap. In addition, 88% also conclude that workplace experience is vital.</li></ul><p>Experience in cooperating with university and schools demonstrates that an effective solution requires many strands including:</p><ul><li>Assisting university in their endeavours to use new approach such as Project Based Learning in the engineering curricula</li><li>Supporting research programme and initiatives. These include endowing chairs and supporting senior researchers as well as continuous support of PhD level research programme.</li><li>Developing relevant curricula with high schools to ensure that there is a steady stream of candidates for STEM subjects </li><li>Encouraging and supporting extra-curricular national and international student contests. </li></ul><p>The paper sets out the current view of the "gap" from industrialist's perspective and will demonstrate that experience of using many of the mitigation strategies have a significant impact in narrowing it.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0110</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>The development of a bridge course Numerical Analysis into the e-learning environment MUMIE</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Maths in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Joanna Daudt</u>, Kees Vuik, Fons Daalderop, Robert van Kints <em>TU Delft, Delft, The Netherlands</em></p><p></p><p>In the frame work of student mobility bridge courses for incoming master student from other engineering schools, become more and more important. Bridge courses are meant to narrow the gap between the knowledge and understanding from student and the demands necessary in the advanced math master courses. Using an e-learning environment makes the bridge course flexible and open to adjustments and extension.</p><p>Together with three other university partners (Aalto University Finland, KTH Sweden and TU Berlin), the TU Delft has made a start end 2012 with the development of a bridge course Numerical Analysis. Other bridge courses are developed by the other partners (Scientific Computing with Matlab, Probability and Statistics, bridge material Math for incoming bachelor student).</p><p>MUMIE is an open source e-learning platform. It uses modern web technology, is written in java and supports any kind of multimedia components (interactive visualizations, audio, video). MUMIE is multi-lingual supporting presently German and English. Learners need nothing but a standard browser. Authors write their content in an comfortable authoring environment based on an eclipse plugin and write mathematical text in the standard Latex (MUMIE-dialect).</p><p>In this paper we report the result and evaluation of a pilot study performed in May 2013 where the developed material was offered to 100 student from the Civil Engineering Department.</p><p>The pilot was successfully implemented, covering the theory for non-linear equations and numerical quadrature together with two homework exercises for bisection, two exercises for fixed point methods and an exercise for integral approximation.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0111</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Engineering positioning test in Flanders: a powerful predictor for study success?</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Attractiveness of Engineering</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal">Jef Vanderoost, Riet Callens, Joos Vandewalle, <u>Tinne De Laet</u> <em>KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium</em></p><p>A new positioning test for BSc Engineering was broadly and uniformly implemented in Flanders in the summer of 2013. The non-mandatory test measures the ability of future engineering student to solve engineering problems and compares a student's mathematical skills with the required previous knowledge.  The positioning test was organized twice during the summer of 2013 and drew 859 participants across three Flemish university. The resulting scores were normally distributed with 56% passing the test. Of all student enrolled for the Bsc of Engineering at KU Leuven, 51% passed the position test, 22% failed, and 27% didn't participate.</p><p>Our goal is to relate the study result to the score on the positioning test, determine the predictive power of the positioning test, discover different student groups that show similar evolution, and determine the impact of the positioning test on enrolment. We analyzed the result of the positioning test, intermediate tests, and the exams in January (1st semester).</p><p>The study leads to the following conclusions:   student with a score lower than 10/20 have a low chance to obtain good result in January (77% badly fails). Their prior knowledge deficiency can't be re-mediated in only one semester.</p><p> While passing the positioning test increases the chance on study success it Is not no guarantee for study success. Other features such as motivation, study effort, study method, and stress-handling are important.</p><ul><li>Despite its predictive power the positioning test does not succeed in advising student that badly fail the test against enrolment.</li></ul><p></p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0112</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Diversity and the academic engineering positioning test in Flanders: Impact on female student and student with disabilities</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Issues of Gender and Diversity</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal">Jef Vanderoost, Riet Callens, Joos Vandewalle, <u>Tinne De Laet</u> <em>KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium</em></p><p>A new positioning test for BSc Engineering was broadly and uniformly implemented in Flanders in the summer of 2013. The non-mandatory test measures the ability of future engineering student to solve engineering problems and compares a student's mathematical skills with the required previous knowledge. The goal of this paper is to study the impact of the positioning test for two target groups: student with disabilities and female student.</p><p>The positioning test uses an inclusive approach regarding student with disabilities. One of the findings it 77% of the student with disabilities that entered the bachelor studies passed the positioning test (compared to the general success rate of 75%), showing that the inclusive approach is successful.</p><p>The study regarding the target group of female student leads to these conclusions:  Female student have a significantly lower success rate than male student. This can be explained by the number of hours in mathematics in secondary education.</p><p> Regarding the impact of negative marking female student have a significantly higher number of blank answers. This is in accordance with literature, which attributes this effect to the more risk-averse behaviour of female student.</p><p> Female student score lower on questions requiring graphical and spatial reasoning. But, they score higher on questions requiring analytic skills and questions testing the application of mathematical theorems taught in secondary school.</p><p> The impact of positioning test result on the decision whether or not to enrol in the BSc Engineering studies does not differ significantly between male and female student.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0113</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>From word-clouds to video: IT tools in the service of learning</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Pedro Neto</u><sup>1</sup>, Bill Williams<sup>1
                    ,2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Setubal Polytechnic Institute, Setubal, Portugal,<sup> 2</sup>CEG-IST, Instituto Superior T?ico, Universidade de Lisboa, Lisbon, Portugal</em></p><p>Working within a theoretical framework drawn from Etienne Wenger s technology stewardship concept, the authors describe six technology-based approach they have implemented to facilitate active and collaborative learning. First they describe a procedure to employ Word Cloud technology to enhance learner formative reflection in the classroom. Then ways of using a Learning Management System in tandem with online Self and Peer Assessment tools to enhance collaborative learning in groups and between groups is addressed. In addition, the authors describe how MS Powerpoint can be used by learners along with webcams and free video editing tools to enable student team preparation of evaluated video presentations.</p><p>The paper describes the tools used, the setting up of the activities and data-gathering procedures used with first year undergraduate civil engineering student</p><p>Keywords: technology stewardship, active learning; collaborative learning, IT tools, pedagogy, word clouds</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0114</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Curriculum Development to Sustain Retention and Graduation Rates</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Norman Loney</u> <em>New Jersey Institute of technology, Newark, New Jersey, USA</em></p><p>At New Jersey Institute of Technology the first year curriculum for the engineering student all contained Calculus I, Physics I with Laboratory and General Chemistry I rounding out to a total of 17 credits in the first semester. The second semester contained 19 credits including Calculus II, Physics II and Laboratory, General Chemistry II and Laboratory as well as Computer Science. Although the retention rates for chemical engineers were not terrible (88%), we strived to improve and decided on three modifications that we anticipated would increase the retention rates. In the fall 2011, the chemical engineering curriculum was modified in order to sustain retention and graduation rates by making three deliberate changes. Firstly, the broadly accepted notion that engineering physics is to be calculus based suggest that Physics I should be offered subsequent to Calculus I. This change was implemented by swapping physics with a social science in the first semester. The second step was to ensure connections between the fundamentals of engineering design (FED-101) course and the writing course. The third change required moving Physics II to the penultimate semester in which the subject matter would be prerequisite for the process control course. As a result we observed that our retention rate increased to 93%. Simultaneously, the physics department has been also observing that the physics II course is now composed of more mature student that are engaged as if the material is more relevant to some project or course work.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0115</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Reforming Engineering Education - A feasibility analysis of Models for Innovation</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Anders Berglund</u><sup>1</sup>, Sofia Ritz<sup>1</sup>, Jonte Bernhard<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>KTH Royal Institute of Technology, Stockholm, Sweden,<sup> 2</sup>Link??g University, Norrkoping, Sweden</em></p><p>The capability to innovate is an important skill for engineers, thus stressing the critical issue of educating for innovation at technical university. This paper investigates the feasibility of four different models for implementing and practising new content in engineering education. Implementation efforts are looked at revealing systematic constraints and pitfalls, and also evaluating these approach from the perspective of innovation capabilities and the desired effects from changes in education. The different models can be categorized as bottom-up and top-down approach depending on actors' roles in the education system. The top-down and bottom-up approach are also categorized in accordance to the width of the approach: programmatic changes with new content in many courses and specialized changes with new courses addressing the desired content and capabilities. A critical analysis is made of the four models intercepting specific learning elements that can be elevated to facilitate innovation in courses and programs. The critical analysis not only relates to educational values, but also relates more specifically to the needs of teaching and training innovation and consequently to developing innovation capabilities. This leads us to discuss the practical epistemologies involved in engineering practice in general and in innovation in particular; engineering as an art and as a science and both are essential. Finally arguments on how to actually reform education are addressed, with attention on leveraging innovation as a key driver to excel and challenge the learning experiences faced by current and future student.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0116</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Deeper approach to learning with peer-assessment</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: student as partners</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Katja Vahtikari</u>, Anne L?eenm?, Panu Kiviluoma <em>Aalto University, Espoo, Finland</em></p><p>The focus of this paper is on peer assessment and the effect of assessment on learning. In addition, student' insights and experiences of peer-assessment are explored. The authors' goal is to use assessment as a tool for guiding student' work to a desirable direction. Letting student get involved in assessment and defining the assessment criteria helps them take responsibility of their learning and build up confidence, commitment, and ownership. Could peer assessment encourage the student to reflect on questions such as am I doing the right thing or is this enough, and, as a result, activate them to analyse and enhance their performance?</p><p>The student' perspectives on assessment were collected with a survey and feedback from courses taught by the authors. For example, student were asked how they experience and value peer assessment, what is its effect on learning, what kind of support and instructions are needed, and do they feel competent assessing their peers. This paper introduces experiences from three courses at the schools of Engineering, Electrical Engineering, and Chemical Technology of Aalto University. The courses are Experimental methods, Integrated Interior Wooden Surfaces, and Astronomical View of the World. They vary in extent both in terms of duration and credits. The smallest course is three credits (82h) and the largest five credits (135h). The number of student varies from 20 to 60.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0119</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>The acceptance of using an annotation approach on Tablet PC-based e-book in a mechanical engineering course</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Technology in Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Poster</p><p class="MsoNormal">Chia-Ju Liu<sup>1</sup>, Hsin-Chin Chen<sup>2</sup>, Ming-Hsun Shen<sup>1</sup>, Yueh-Min Huang<sup>2</sup>, <u>Tzone-I Wang</u><sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Graduate Institute of Science Education and Environmental Education, National Kaohsiung Normal University, Kaohsiung, Taiwan,<sup> 2</sup>Department of Engineering Science, National Cheng Kung University, Tainan, Taiwan</em></p><p>Tablet PCs have become prevalent learning devices, widely used by learners in a variety of mobile learning environments nowadays. Many studies have explored the feasibility of using Tablet PCs in the learning engineering courses, especially those with complex graphics or operation processes. Of them, mechanism is a fundamental course to introduce the concepts of the mechanical components in the field of mechanical engineering. For the course, printed books have been a major media for student to learn in the traditional classrooms. However, printed books have their limitations in presenting scalable architectures or the dynamic process of mechanical operation thoroughly, compromising the learning interest and effectiveness. In order to enhance student  learning motivation and understanding of learning Mechanism, this study proposes using the Tablet PC-based e-book, which supports text, graphics, video and interactive functions to facilitate student an adaptive learning environment. Furthermore, interactive annotation functions were constructed on this interactive e-book learning environment to assist learners in highlighting important potions of the learning content for effective future review. To verify the effectiveness of the proposewd approach, a questionnaire was developed to evaluate learning satisfaction, learning interest and technology acceptance. The findings indicated that adopting the interative e-book system literally elicted student  interest in learning the Mechanism course, where many architecture concepts and dynamicprocesses of mechanical operation became more illustrative, especially by the aid of annotation functions provided.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0120</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>A model of critical reflectionwithin awork based learning programme</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Continuing Engineering Education and Lifelong learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Bill Glew</u> <em>Aston University, Birmingham, UK</em></p><p></p><p>The increasing use of active learning activities for the education, training and development of engineers has brought into focus the need to understand the ways in which engineers learn from experience across a range of environments. Since 2006 the Engineering Council has been leading their Gateways Project which uses work based learning, a particular form of active learning, to accelerate and make more widely accessible the opportunity to develop and demonstrate professional engineering competences by their incorporation into a range of academic programme. However during the development of both MSc and BEng programme within this Project it became apparent that existing models of learning could not adequately articulate the learning experience being generated by the programme. In order to maximise the benefits to learners from a the wide range of backgrounds and differing engineering environments by fully utilising the inherent flexibility of the programme a more representative model was needed. Critical reflection on the experience of developing the programme provided the basis for the development of that model.</p><p>This paper presents the findings of that critical reflection and the resulting model that has been generated as a result. The paper includes a discussion of the role of critical reflection within the model and the impact of its role on the study experiences of learners. So as to elucidate the model's relevance, the paper includes a short case study aspect of one learner's experience. Finally the paper concludes with description of the current work to further enhance the model s utility.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0121</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>The Effects of using Synonyms Annotation for English Video Subtitles on Content Understanding, Vocabulary Learning, and Cognitive Loading</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Technology in Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Tzone I WANG</u>, In Hong Wu <em>National Cheng Kung University, Taiwan, Tainan, Taiwan</em></p><p>Video watching is now a popular way of learning for many disciplines. Many researches have proved that learners may achieve better performance when watching proper videos than taking traditional classroom courses. The Internet now makes it easier for learners to access online videos with information on various new technology for self-learning. However, for English as Foreign Language learners, their limited volume of English vocabulary might pose as a barrier to understand videos with difficult contents and subtitles. Researchers have been using dictionary style full explanations on the vocabulary of video subtitles for learners while they are watching videos. Cognitive load would increase when a learner has to stops to read the full explanations of unfamiliar words in the subtitle while watching a video; researchers has shown that increased cognitive load would lead to the reduction of a learner s performance.</p><p></p><p>This study propose a new method to reduce learners  cognitive load when learning with videos. When a learner clicks on an unfamiliar vocabulary in the subtitle of a playing video the video stops and the method displays as many as possible the synonyms, instead of the full explanations, of the vocabulary for the learner. To see whether the method is feasible and effective, this study conducts two experiments on college student using videos of different difficulty levels. The experiment result confirm that the simple way of annotating vocabulary with synonyms not only reduces cognitive load of learners but also increases their understanding of video contents and volume of vocabulary effectively.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0122</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Mid Project Milestone for the QUEECA TEMPUS Project: First result and Rising Expectations.</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Quality Assurance and Accreditation</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal">Claudio Borri, Michele Betti, <u>Elisa Guberti</u> <em>Universit?egli Studi di Firenze - Civil and Environ. Engineering Dpt., Firenze, Italy</em></p><p>The QUEECA (Quality of Engineering Education in Central Asia) TEMPUS project main aim is that one of setting up and starting implementing a system of quality assurance (QA) of engineering education in Central Asia (CA), finalised to the accreditation of engineering programme by the award of the EUR-ACE quality label on the basis of the EUR-ACE Framework Standards and related quality requirements and procedures. The project also takes advantage of experience in the EHEA (through ENAEE) and current efforts in Central Asia countries. More specifically QUEECA aims to use as basis the EUR-ACE Framework Standards (EAFS) and related quality requirements and procedures, awarding the EUR-ACE quality label to the accredited programme. At the present moment (March 2014) the project has arrived to the mid project milestone and time has come for a thorough internal evaluation taking into account the first encouraging result so far obtained, such as the creation of the Kyrgyz Society for engineering Education (October 2013) and the rising expectations from the concerned parties. The paper shortly introduces the QUEECA TEMPUS project and reports about the achieved result and the activities scheduled for the next moths. Finally the reasons why the project is to be considered a pilot one, introducing the EUR-ACE system outside the European Union with an easy replicable model are also given.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0123</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Electronic Engineering PBL at the Design Engineering School of Valencia, Spain</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Poster</p><p class="MsoNormal">Enrique Ballester Sarrias, Javier Ib?z Civera, Rafael Masot Peris, Miguel Alca??Fillo, Jos?arrigues Baixauli, Jos?icente Lid??oger, <u>Luis M. S?hez Ruiz</u> <em>Universitat Polit?ica de Valencia, Valencia, Spain</em></p><p></p><p>Project based learning methodology(PBL) is one of the most effective methods of teaching where student not only develop the scientific and technical abilities inherent to the corresponding subjects but it also fosters knowledge about organization and management at the same time that it promotes a number of social abilities as valued today as teamwork, leadership, communication, planning, etc.</p><p>This methodology is widely used and tested in many disciplines and it is well-known the UK approach to Engineering Project-Based Learning White Paper sponsored by the Bernard M, Gordon MIT Engineering Leadership Program, MIT</p><p>In this paper we describe PBL experiences carried out in two subjects in two different degrees of the School of Design Engineering ETSID at Valencia (Spain), namely in the subject of "Digital Electronics" at the BEng in Electronics and Control Engineering and in "Electronics Technology" at the BEng in Aerospace Engineering degree.</p><p>student do practical work in a consistent design of an electronic system in groups of two or three student. Teachers propose a project list with an adequate difficulty to the level of knowledge of student and a reasonable execution time after that, in a first step, the objectives and specifications of the prototype are clearly defined.</p><p>In all cases, the projects done by the student, end with the construction of prototypes which are openly exposed to the public in a special session.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0124</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Innovating Engineering Education: The RVS Approach: An Empirically Grounded Method to Improved Practice and Enhanced Student Experience</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Continuing Engineering Education and Lifelong learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Robin Clark</u>, Jane Andrews <em>Aston University, Birmingham, UK</em></p><p></p><p><b>Discussion Paper</b></p><p><b></b></p><p><b>Background</b></p><p>In seeking to address issues associated with difficulties in attracting, recruiting and retaining student onto engineering programme, the paper authors set about developing a bespoke learning and teaching approach that would meet the learning needs and expectations of student, whilst providing a sound pedagogical basis upon which engineering could be taught. Building on Higher Education theory, and grounded in Engineering Education Research and Practise, an approach was developed in which three key components were identified as pivotal to Student Success within Engineering: Relationship: Variety: and, Synergy.  </p><p></p><p><b>Methodology</b></p><p>The RVS approach has been developed and tested over a number of years using a mixed methodological approach within an action research design. This paper presents the research findings in such a way so as to highlight the value of empirically grounded engineering education practice.</p><p></p><p><b>Discussion </b></p><p>When taken together the three components of the RVS approach result in an innovative approach to engineering education that argues that <i>Relationships + Variety + Synergy = Student Success (R+ V + S = S<sup>2</sup></i>). Taking each component of the approach in turn, the discussion focuses on how engineering educators can use each of these components to bring together pedagogic, discipline-related, socio-environmental and individual factors to address the challenges associated with engineering education.</p><p></p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0125</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Tackling Transition! Peer Mentoring in Engineering Education - A UK Perspective </strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Education al Research Methods</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Jane Andrews</u>, Robin Clark <em>Aston University, Birmingham, UK</em></p><p></p><p>Grounded in the research findings of a study which examined the perceptions of engineering student peer mentors and mentees, this discussion paper critically examines the pedagogic and managerial issues encountered in developing and rolling out a bespoke peer mentoring programme aimed at reducing first year attrition in Engineering. Starting with the research question "Does peer mentoring improve engineering student' transition into university?' the study looked closely at two groups of engineering student as they progressed from  freshers' week into the first year of their studies. </p><p><b>Methodology</b></p><p>Following an Action Research Design and utilising an approach to Peer Mentoring developed out of a large international study (Clark and Andrews, 2013; Andrews and Clark, 2011), a mixed methodological approach was utilised to examine student' perceptions of the value of peer mentoring during transition into engineering. This paper presents the findings of the first  research cycle', critically discussing how the study continues to shape and guide practice.</p><p><b>Discussion</b></p><p>The discussion will focus on the social, academic and professional aspects of student transition into university, highlighting the challenges faced by engineering student.Focusing specifically on the challenges associated with studying engineering the discussion considers how the  unknown' nature of the discipline can be particularly disconcerting for new student. It focuses on the unique role played by peer mentoring in helping new student overcome the barriers and challenges of the first term in university, putting forward an empirically grounded model of Peer Mentoring for use in Engineering Faculties. <b></b></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0126</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>integrated project design for Civil Engineering Master in Oporto University</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Engineering Design</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>B?ara Rangel</u><sup>1</sup>, Fernando Brand?Alves<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Engineering Faculty Of University of Porto, Porto, Portugal,<sup> 2</sup>Engineering Faculty Of University of Porto, Porto, Portugal</em></p><p></p><p>The current difficulties in the Construction Industry have been confirming the urgent interdisciplinary between all the design disciplines, from engineering to architecture. The required high levels of building efficiency and the optimization of the building process are increasing the demands on the accuracy of projects. The project is no longer a sum of contributes, but a design methodology that combines the answers to all the different requisites of the building, an INTEGRATED PROJECT. This multidisciplinary approach to the design problems is only possible if it s present in the design process from the first moment. This implicit complicity is only possible if it starts in the university education, searching for the common language of construction.</p><p>In recent years of Civil Engineering Master the discipline of Architecture, has been showing to future engineers this common territory, the construction grammar. Different construction technology imply specific design principals and rules. Different structural systems imply different architectural design. In the lectures, through the architectural history is searched the design lexicon of the different technology. In laboratory, studding real project, making construction models, visiting working sites and talking with architects and engineers, are given the design tools of this integrated project methodology. This article aims to present the experience of recent years developed this course in order to contribute to the increasingly urgent intersection of architecture and engineering.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0127</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>An open approach to educational resource development with a specific example from structural engineering</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Technology in Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Liam Comerford</u>, Marco De Angelis, Adam Mannis, Michael Beer, Ioannis Kougioumtzoglou <em>University of Liverpool, Liverpool, UK</em></p><p>A detailed account of how an interactive learning software package was developed to address a specific knowledge gap amongst undergraduate engineers at the University of Liverpool is presented in this paper. A primary objective, established from the outset, was not only to meet the needs of the local university, but to also consider dissemination and applicability of the resource for other institutions. There were three main objectives: First, the software needed to teach the subject matter with little or no additional input from the lecturer. Second, a system was required to ensure student completed a list of tasks (interactive problems / questions) set in the software, and this could be checked. Finally the software needed to be as accessible as possible for other institutions, home and abroad.  The software package takes the form of a presentation with a series of in-built interactive elements. These elements consist of simulated experiments and questions, requiring input before the user may continue. The primary purpose of these tasks is to keep the student engaged with the material on-screen, i.e. they cannot complete each stage unless they read and understand the task properly. The development team partnered with a number of external institutions, thereby providing a network of academics to offer feedback at every stage. This gave rise to an iterative development procedure, through which the resource has been able to expand from being a narrow institutional-specific application, to now become a comprehensive tool with far-reaching use by others across the international engineering community.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0128</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Computer based examinations at Politecnico di Torino</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Maths in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Anita Tabacco</u><sup>1</sup>, Paolo Boieri<sup>1</sup>, Giorgio Santiano<sup>1
                    ,2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Politecnico di Torino, Torino, Italy,<sup> 2</sup>C.S.I Piemonte, Torino, Italy</em></p><p>The computer tool is becoming increasingly important in authoring, delivering and reporting examinations in the form of multiple choice tests, in particular in the presence of a large number of student. At Politecnico di Torino the Moodle platform is mainly used for Admission Test for Engineering programme, to check the language level of knowledge (English and Italian language for foreign student). Recently it was also used in the context of the course of Mathematical Analysis I (about 5000 student in 20parallel courses); as we describe in this presentation, the choice of a computer based test resulted in the following: a deep review of the course settings and methodology, designed to ensure a greater homogeneity of content between parallel courses; a thorough analysis of the subjects of the verification and of the structure of the test to be administered; the adaptation of the Moodle platform for the needs of Mathematics (for example, entering formulas written in Latex) and a good integration with the  Portale della Didattica , the access point to all services related to the teaching of the Politecnico di Torino granted to student and professors.<p>The result of this four year work, the impact on student and development prospects of this experience are also discussed.</p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0129</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong><i>Professional knowledge, skills and competencies of the new graduates and the engineering professionals   comparison of the significance in working-life</i></strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Continuing Engineering Education and Lifelong learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal">Pirre Hyotynen<sup>1</sup>, <u>Sanja Mursu</u><sup>1</sup>, Jussi-Pekka Teini<sup>2
                    ,1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Academic Engineers and Architects in Finland - TEK, Helsinki, Finland,<sup> 2</sup>Student Union of Tampere University of Technology, Tampere, Finland</em></p><p>Academic Engineers and Architects in Finland - TEK has conducted surveys for M.Sc. graduates of technology or architecture since the early eighties. Nowadays the surveys are made in close cooperation with the Finnish university providing higher education in technology. In addition to those surveys TEK has also conducted surveys on professional development of academic engineers and architects in Finland. The survey on professional development has been conducted six times since 2002. The aim of the survey is to provide knowledge on the needs, attitudes and possibilities for professional development. The information from these two surveys provides TEK an important perspective on the development of engineering education as well as further professional development.</p><p>The aim of this paper is to present an insight into how the knowledge, skills and competencies of the newly graduated engineers have developed through the engineering education and due to working experience gained during studies.</p><p>Secondly, the paper compares the importance of the knowledge, skills and competencies of the new graduates with those of the engineering professionals who have a minimum of 5 years of post-graduate working experience.</p><p></p><p></p><p>This practice-based paper aims at presenting the important working-life skills and competencies in the field of engineering as well as the skills and competencies that should be emphasized in engineering education and further professional development.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0130</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>The role of educational technology and learning spaces in electrical engineering education - a case study at Aalto University School of Electrical Engineering</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Technology in Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Kirsti Keltikangas</u>, Jari J. H?inen <em>Aalto University School of Electrical Engineering, Espoo, Finland</em></p><p></p><p>student of engineering are increasingly using technology in their life. Most of the first-year student have their own laptops when entering university. The capabilities of the student' mobile phones can be far better than of the academic staff. student are connected to the internet with their equipment wherever they are. In addition, the generations who enter university in the next years are very talented in using different types of social media and internet services since their early childhood.</p><p>However, engineering education and its curriculum design is undoubtedly at least one step behind the student' current state. The technology used by the student in various spaces-not only in formal teaching ones-should be taken into account and its opportunities integrated into engineering education. At present, the current spaces used in teaching are often old-fashioned lecture theatres not equipped with state-of-the-art technology. The academic staff does use sufficiently mobile and online learning as an option when developing their courses.</p><p>A case study (n=236) was completed at Aalto University School of Electrical Engineering on how much engineering student use technology in their formal and informal learning. The survey covered the spaces used for learning as well. The result will gain insight into the student' thinking and will help teachers in the curriculum design. The result will also help the campus development managers in planning the renovation of the School's teaching spaces to support modern ways of learning.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0131</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Tools to see with: Investigating the role of experimental technology for student learning in the laboratory</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Technology in Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Jonte Bernhard</u> <em>Link??g University, Norrk??g, Sweden</em></p><p>BACKGROUND: student  experience of the world in the laboratory is not a direct experience, human   world, but a mediated experience, human   tool   world, shaped by the use of physical and symbolic tools. Technology is used as agencies of observations, i.e. as tools for collection and processing of physical data. However, the role of experimental technology for student learning in the laboratory is largely neglected in educational research. If technology are studied at all, it is often seen as being synonymous with studying the role of computers.</p><p>METHODS: student  interaction in different physics and electric circuit labs, with different experimental technology, was recorded using digital camcorders. The videotaped data were used to detect typical interactional patterns. Particularly interesting parts of these sessions were transcribed to allow for detailed examination of interactional patterns.</p><p>result: In some cases the technology were used as tools to see the world with and some aspects of the world were put in the foreground. In other cases the technology in itself become the focus of attention and no, or inadequate, connection to the world was made. The role of the technology for student  learning depended in some cases on the affordances of the technology used, but in other cases it depended on the pedagogical design.</p><p></p><p>CONCLUSION: Some experimental technology are more effective for facilitating learning by being effective tools to see with. However, for the effective use of technology the educational design is important and no technology is effective independently of the pedagogy used.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0133</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Teaching self-awareness, diversity and reflection to support an integrated engineering curriculumaugmented with problem and scenario-based learning.</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Active Learning</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Emanuela Tilley</u><sup>1</sup>, Jan Peters<sup>2</sup>, John E. Mitchell<sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>UCL Engineering, London, UK,<sup> 2</sup>Katalytik, Christchurch, UK</em></p><p>A newfound student-centred Strengths Programme is currently being designed to provide student with a set of tools and the vocabulary to help them identify, explore, question, utilise,develop and reflect on their personal strengths and natural talents throughout their undergraduate engineering career. Through such exercise, student become familiar with a common language, used by employers, and obtain a heightened awareness of each other's potential when contributing to shared team goals. It will equip them with the ability to deal with and possibly prevent problems associated with leadership and assignment of roles, division of responsibility, time management and communication often experienced when working in teams. Additionally, addressing this level of self-awareness, student build mutual respect and motivation; the programme is designed to produce graduates that are more easily attuned to the values shared by top employers in diversity and inclusivity. StrengthsFinder2.0, published by GallupPress, is a strengths-based personal profiling and self-assessment tool that is introduced and explored to give the student a chance at understanding the type of engineering activities they enjoy and feel they can excel in. Helping to realise their unique potential to successfully take on leadership roles and understand the value in pursuing roles of  leadership beyond authority', is also regarded as a pivotal motive for a revamp and redesign of the current engineering curriculum. Positive feedback and enthusiasm to get involved as  Champions' for various aspects of the Strengths Programme have been bestowed by current student who have undertaken isolated pilots aligned with existing Year I problem-based learning modules.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0136</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>A statistical method for assessing teaching effectiveness based on non-identical pre- and post-tests</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Education al Research Methods</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Julie Direnga</u>, Dion Timmermann, Andrea Brose, Christian Kautz <em>Hamburg University of Technology, Hamburg, Germany</em></p><p>Diagnostic tests and concept inventories are widely used in science and engineering education to monitor the effectiveness of teaching [1]. Often, identical tests are given before and after instruction, allowing direct comparison of respective scores [2]. However, in many introductory engineering courses, post-tests require familiarity with technical terminology and are therefore not feasible as pre-tests. Conversely, pre-tests that measure prerequisite knowledge but do not use technical terms may also not sufficiently cover the topics taught. In many cases, this discourages the use of identical pre- and post-tests. For identical pre- and post-tests, a relative learning gain factor has been proposed [3]. This relative gain has been used to establish the difference in effectiveness of traditional and active-learning approach [3]. In case of non-identical pre- and post-tests, a new approach has to be developed to compare the effectiveness of various teaching methods. We propose a statistical method for treating result from non-identical tests to assess and compare the influence of instruction. We test this method on an 8-year data set and critically discuss the result and validity. A comparison to established measures for teaching effectiveness is made.</p><p>[1] http://www.cihub.org [2] Steif, P. S., and Hansen, M. (2006). Comparisons between performances in a statics concept inventory and course examinations. International Journal of Engineering Education, 22(5), 1070. [3] Hake, R. R. (1998). Interactive-engagement versus traditional methods: A six-thousand-student survey of mechanics test data for introductory physics courses. American journal of Physics, 66(1), 64-74.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0140</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>An Insight to Global Engineering Challenges: Study and Analysis</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: student as partners</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Rohit Kandakatla</u><sup>1</sup>, Joseph Packhem<sup>2</sup>, David D. Delaine<sup>3</sup>, Dhinesh Balaji Radhakrishnan<sup>4</sup>, Claudio Freitas<sup>5</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>KG Reddy college of Engineering and Technology, Hyderabad, Andhra Pradhesh, India,<sup> 2</sup>Marquette University, Milwaukee, WI, USA,<sup> 3</sup>University of Sao Paolo, S?Paulo, SP, Brazil,<sup> 4</sup>University of Petroleum and Energy Studies, Dehradun, India,<sup> 5</sup>State University of Campinas, S?Paulo, SP, Brazil</em></p><p>Academics across the globe have been constantly improving Engineering education methodologies for many years. There have been many organizations and, initiatives that have come up for this very purpose. International Federation of Engineering Education Societies (IFEES) and Student Platform for Engineering Education Development (SPEED) are two such organization which work to the improve the quality of engineering education provided to the student. While both these organizations work for the same cause, they take a completely different approach. IFEES concentrates on a more top-down approach where as SPEED believes in a bottom-top approach giving student the role to bring about a change in the system. This paper portrays one initiative that IFEES and SPEED have taken together to analyze the various engineering problems currently faced by student across the globe. This analysis is based on a survey which is provided to student from many countries to raise the various issues, problems and challenges they are facing in the current education system. The result of this analysis will be used by both IFEES and SPEED separately, which will be addressed later in their respective approach to benefit the student fraternity. This analysis will also provide a comparison between the various engineering trends and methodologies practiced in different countries.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0141</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>DEVELOPMENT OF AN ENVIRONMENTAL AND RESOURCES ENGINEERING LEARNING</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Either</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Enrica Caporali</u><sup>1</sup>, Claudio Borri<sup>1</sup>, Atanasko Tuneski<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, University of Firenze, Firenze, Italy,<sup> 2</sup>Faculty of Mechanical Engineering, Ss. Cyril and Methodius University, Skopje, Macedonia</em></p><p></p><p>The European Commission promotes the TEMPUS - Trans European Mobility Programme for University Studies in order to contribute to the creation of an area of cooperation in higher education between the European Union and the Partner Countries (PC). Modernisation of curricula in academic disciplines is one of the TEMPUS priority themes. DEREL - Development of Environment and Resources Engineering is a TEMPUS project leaded by the University of Firenze (UNIFI), Italy, for the period 10/2010 - 06/2014. The DEREL Consortium consists of 11 university (4 EU and 7 PC), and 7 non-academic institutions. The project introduced a new, up to date, postgraduate second level curriculum in Environment and Resources Engineering at DEREL PC university: Ss Cyril and Methodius University in Skopje - UKIM (FYR of Macedonia), University of Novi \Sad - UNS (Serbia) and Polytechnic University of Tirana - PUT (Albania), based on the European Credit Transfer System and in accordance with the Bologna Process, following the conditions for setting up a Double Postgraduate Degree. The project also implemented a sustainable regional network aimed to offer lifelong learning seminars for environment and resources engineering education and training of interested stakeholders, and to organize workshops focused on strengthening the links in the knowledge triangle: environment education-innovation-research. The three agreements between UNIFI with UKIM, with UNS, and with PUT for the establishment of shared educational paths in the environmental programs, aimed at awarding double degree titles between UNIFI and DEREL PC university, is one of the significant concluding objectives of the project.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0142</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Environmental engineering education: examples of accreditation and quality assurance</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Quality Assurance and Accreditation</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Either</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Enrica Caporali</u>, Marcantonio Catelani, Giampaolo Manfrida, Juna Valdiserri <em>School of Engineering, University of Firenze, Firenze, Italy</em></p><p></p><p>Environmental engineers respond to the challenges posed by a growing population, intensified land-use, natural resources exploitation as well as rapidly evolving technology. The environmental engineers must develop technically sound solutions with the aims of maintaining or improving environmental quality, complying with public policy, and optimizing the utilization of resources. The globalization of challenges and problems to be faced leads to the globalization of the engineering profession which requires not only the capacity to communicate in a common technical language, but also the assurance of an adequate and common level of technical competences, knowledge and understanding. The application of the accreditation model EUR-ACE, and of the National Italian Degree Courses Accreditation System to the multidisciplinary first cycle degree in Civil, Building and Environmental Engineering and the more specific second cycle degree in Environmental Engineering carried out at the University of Firenze is presented. Particularly, the critical issues to assure the quality and the status of environmental engineering graduates, in terms of applying knowledge capacities and technical innovative competences, according to the more engineering focused EUR-ACE skill descriptors as well as to the Dublin descriptors, are compared. In addition, the involvement of the student and the professional working world in the definition of learning outcomes and expected skills, the assessment of the system for educating engineers in communicating knowledge and understanding, making informed judgments and choices, capacities to lifelong learning and the promotion of innovative aspects related to the environmental engineering education are further investigated.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0143</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Course Project  My future individual educational trajectory  as a Basis for the Personality-oriented Professional Training</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Olga Belyaeva</u>, Alla Frolkova, Valeriy Solomonov <em>Lomonosov Moscow University of Fine Chemical Technology (MUTHT), Moscow, Russia</em></p><p></p><p></p><p>This paper describes an investigation of the impact of first-year student' motivation towards conceptual understanding of purposes of their individual curriculum adjustment suitable for their future professional career.</p><p></p><p>The multi-level education system of professional training in science-based chemical engineering has been tested and developed since 1997 up to the present in Lomonosov Moscow University of Fine Chemical Technology (MUTHT).</p><p>Motivated and adequate for particular person s capabilities choice of student for differently targeted educational programs is the main goal of the University at the first educational level. The course project "My future individual educational trajectory" has been tested during the second semester of the first year for three years by now. The project is targeted at increasing motivation for technical education, development of communication skills, capability to work as a team, encouraging student to think over the choice of specialty group for the Bachelor s Degree, choice of preferable curricula set for future University years and planning their professional career.</p><p>Still the student not always understand the perspectives of their future profession, are not enough motivated for scientific and engineering work, are often unable of critical self-evaluation which leads to underestimation of future difficulties in mastering the chosen education program.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0146</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Involving student in curriculum development</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Radoslaw Czahajda</u><sup>2</sup>, Natalia Mazur<sup>3</sup>, Marija Stanojevic<sup>1</sup>, Giovanna Campogiani<sup>4</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>Local BEST Group Belgrade, Belgrade, Serbia,<sup> 2</sup>Local BEST Group Wroclaw, Wroclaw, Poland,<sup> 3</sup>Local BEST Group Trondheim, Trondheim, Norway,<sup> 4</sup>Local BEST Group Rome, Rome, Italy</em></p><p>Through events and surveys, BEST (Board of European student of Technology) makes student aware of how they affect engineering education. BEST strives to have an impact not only on student but also on Higher Educational Institutions. We feel responsible for the development of our own curricula as we are the ones who are experiencing drawbacks firsthand.</p><p>In 2012-13 BEST conducted a survey among 2234 European engineering student. Out of those, only 55% ever had the possibility to evaluate their educational programme. 87% of them evaluated university courses and just 8% evaluated European Educational System. Only 5-10% of the evaluation is done through discussions while the rest is done online or through paper-forms. Even though student are asked for their opinion, 66% of all believe that university does not value it.</p><p>BEST events, such as Events on Education (EoEs) and Local Events on Educations (LEoEs) are an opportunity to exchange opinions amongst participants. Both formats aim to confront student, professors and company representatives on educational topics, through discussion groups, workshops and other interactive activities. While EoEs involve international student and focus on European issues, LEoEs aim at student of a single university and focus on the local educational environment.   Evaluation of aforementioned events shows that gained outcomes are valuable for all stakeholders. Following paper will present and compare methods used to collect student input as well as differences among outcomes and their dissemination. Moreover benefits of organising such events will be discussed as we'd like them to become a common practice.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0147</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Towards a continuous assessment of mathematical competences in a First Year of Aerospace Engineering</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Maths in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Either</p><p class="MsoNormal">Francisco Minguez, J.A. Mora??M.D. Rosell<u>Luis M. S?hez Ruiz</u> <em>Universitat Polit?ica de Val?ia, Valencia, Spain</em></p><p>Assessing mathematical competences is always a difficult issue, particularly in the first year of university engineering degrees when student with different backgrounds are learning together. The grade that student receive matters to all of them and should reflect as accurately as possible their degree of achievement. student should be aware that acquisition of mathematical competences is a continuous process and that any failure or problem they might face will be a sign of two facts: firstly and quite likely that they did not achieve in the past the expected competences and, secondly, that they are in a handicapped position to continue. Reversely, any successful achievement of expected competences in due time will place them in an advanced position toward achieving upper levels of knowledge in Mathematics and other subjects. On the other hand grading is a discreet process that comes from pictures taken through their "moments of evaluation" carried out by means of activities, lab classes, exams,... and should reflect the effort developed by the student in due time as well as the competences shown at each moment of the topic under study and, not to be dismissed, the competences whose specific "moments of evaluations" have already been done in the past. We expose how these ideas may be taken into account in order to carry out the process of grading mathematics competences achievement in the first year of the Aerospace Engineering degree at the School of Design Engineering in Valencia.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0149</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Study Ability Through Engagement</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: student as partners</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Sanna Unkuri</u>, Laura Heinonen, Eeva Myller <em>Aalto University Student Union, Espoo, Finland</em></p><p>Study ability is a student's working ability. It influences learning result, study success and well-being of the student and the study community. The Kyky project is coordinated by the National Union of University student in Finland (SYL). Other project partners include the Aalto University and the University of Tampere and their corresponding student unions.</p><p>The objective of the project is to establish the promotion of study ability as permanent part of university communities' activities and advance student integration, student participation and the work of student associations.</p><p> The material provides academic communities with information and incentives in order to increase study ability and study engagement. Study engagement is promoted through four themes: 1) Engagement and inspiration, 2) Trying and daring, 3) Competent and coping, and 4) Being well and taking care. The material is intended to be used at communities such as faculties, subject associations, student associations and organisations as well as various development groups.</p><p></p><p></p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0150</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Entrepreneurship and Lean Manufacturing for Software Engineering.</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Global Engineer</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Carlos Rioja del R</u>, Arturo Morgado Est?z, Juan Jos?om?uez Jim?z <em>University of C?z, Andalusia, Spain</em></p><p>One of the goals of Engineering Education is the education of our student and job performance in the labor market. For that, we introduce several related aspects focused on Software Engineering. As usual, when we talk about "Software", we talk about an intangible product, so we?l try to give an approach of concepts like Canvas Model, or Value Stream Mapping, but for Software Engineers.</p><p></p><p>Several success cases and entrepreneurship examples (using these tools) will be introduced too. Most of them, from the University of C?z (South Spain).</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0151</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>The influence of the Crisis on the future of the European Higher Education Area</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Sustainability in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Urbano Dom?uez</u><sup>1</sup>, Jes??agdaleno<sup>2</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>University of Valladolid, Valladolid, Spain,<sup> 2</sup>University of Valladolid, Valladolid, Spain</em></p><p>For years cuts in public funding have been implemented in many European university. Moreover, additional cuts are applied, trying to cope with the economic crisis and to reduce public deficits.</p><p> Those cuts are affecting some basic pillars of the European Union, which is not only a political and economic structure but also a social construction. With reference to the EHEA, the social dimension means equal opportunities for people in having an education of quality, and it is focussed in facilitating access and outcomes independently of the socio- economic background of student, and other factors which may lead to educational disadvantage. The Bologna process also considered social objectives in the building of the EHEA.</p><p> In some countries severe reductions in grants and study loans have been introduced at a time when registration fees have suffered a substantial increase. Also, the number of teachers has been reduced, they have more lecture hours and their salaries are falling. The authors discuss the effects of these cuts and analyze how a double segregation in EHE is being enhanced: nationally, for student from more deprived groups, and across the EHEA, for countries with bigger financial problems with respect to those who are better off. Some corrective measures are also discussed with a special focus on Engineering Education.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0152</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Entrepreneurship Road Show - Promoting Entrepreneurship at Engineering Universitie</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Entrepreneurship of Employability</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Pirre Hyotynen</u>, Martti Kivioja <em>Academic Engineers and Architects in Finland TEK, Helsinki, Finland</em></p><p>Academic Engineers and Architects in Finland - TEK actively works towards enhancing entrepreneurship and entrepreneurial skills of engineering student as well as working professionals. One of the recent actions includes a road show in university of engineering education that was organized in six university during 2013. This paper presents the targets, concept and result of the tour.   In 2012 TEK conducted a master thesis study aiming to evaluate the current state of entrepreneurship education in Finnish university of technology and offer tools to develop it. One of the main targets of the road show was to distribute the result of this study. Alongside this, the target of the events was to promote entrepreneurship in general. The work shop style events brought together teachers, student, professionals and other stakeholders interested in entrepreneurship to share knowledge, ideas and best practices.</p><p>The road show events were organized in close cooperation with the university and student entrepreneurship societies, local entrepreneurship stakeholders and individual entrepreneurs. To have real life entrepreneurs as speakers was considered vital for the marketing and the content of the events. The main concept was similar in all road show events. The events included presentations, working group sessions, common discussion and networking dinner. The input was reported in a form of best practices or most crucial challenges. The participants appreciated especially the following: a chance to network with people interested in entrepreneurship, peer support and encouragement for entrepreneurial career, and best practices on how university can develop entrepreneurial skills of student.</p><p></p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0154</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>What makes a counterexample exemplary?</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Maths in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Chih Hsien Huang</u> <em>Ming Chi University of Technology, New Taipei City, Taiwan</em></p><p>This paper explored how first-year engineering student generated examples for statements believed to be true and counterexamples for statements believed to be false. This study based on the perspective that "examples as a research tool that provides a  window' into a learner's mind". The participants comprised 112 first-year engineering student at a university of technology in Taiwan who previously completed courses of derivative and definite integrals. The questionnaire contained three false mathematical statements, and was designed to assess student ability to generate counterexamples regarding differentiation and integration. The primary data sources were the written responses to the questionnaire and interviews. Semi-structured interviews were carried out with 15 engineering student.</p><p>In this study, the engineering student could not generate proper counterexamples to refute the false mathematical statements. They often fail to check that the conditions are satisfied. this is because they are not fluent in using appropriate terms, notations, properties, or do not recognize the role of such conditions. To improve the understanding of engineering student regarding calculus concepts, teachers must understand student' misconceptions and spend additional time interpreting relevant concepts. Counterexamples can be used for assessment of learners' understanding in a broad sense. Furthermore, uses of counterexamples for teaching, in selecting instructional examples it is important to take into account learners' preconceptions and misconceptions. In our opinion, the power of these examples is also testified by the fact that they tend to impress in the memory of student, because of their peculiar features, thus further helping their learning process.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0156</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>The Changing Role of university in the 21st Century - Teachers and Learners Needs</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Either</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Anik??lm</u> <em>Budapest University of Technology and Economics, Budapest, Hungary</em></p><p>The aim of this presentation is to provide an insight into the role of higher education in the information-driven world regarding how to best satisfy the needs of teachers and learners.  Between 2009-2011 the Budapest University of Technology and Economics implemented the SROP project Training of trainers at the Budapest University of Technology and Economics" The general aim of the project was contributing to the reduction of those missing trainer competences that are necessary for the implementation of the requirements of the Bologna-process, the European Qualifications Framework and the LLL strategy. The trainings realized within the frameworks of the project were based on a previous needs assessment of the institute. The internal survey served the purpose of having a comprehensive picture on the relevant training needs within the teaching staff.  Another survey regarding the training needs of teaching and administrative staff in Hungarian higher education is connected with the MELLearN Network (Hungarian University Lifelong Learning Network). One of the main aims of Network is to have a comprehensive picture on the training needs of trainers and staff working in higher education, and initiating trainings that provide the necessary skills, knowledge required by them. In the autum2012 members of the association decided to establish a training database to satisfy arising training needs of teachers and workers of partner institutions. This common training database, being the first phase of the survey, ensures the optimal use of institutional resources and wider range of available training opportunities. In the 2. phase (spring, 2013) we investigated the training needs of instructors and workers via online survey. This survey based on the experiences of the previous research at Budapest University of Technology and Economics. Our research aimed to reveal the use of different teaching methods, ways of organizing education among participant and their training needs. 734 instructors and administrative staff filled in the online questionnaire from 18 higher educational institutions. Having a collaborative partnership with the University of Oulu, the survey was also conducted in Finland in autumn 2013, using the same pattern, and a comparative analysis was done to evaluate the differences and similarities of Hungarian and Finnish training needs. On the basis of the result MELLearN Association aims to develop its training database in accordance with revealed training needs. Almost every university is continuously working on to find out, how to improve the efficiency of the educational process. But first we have to investigate the learning attitude, the formal and non-formal learning habits of the student and understand the main characteristics of the educational processes within the institution. Therefore, after the first two surveys on teachers' and administrative staff's training needs, the Budapest University of Technology and Economics conducted an online survey among its student to learn more about their learning habits. Almost one third of the 20,000 student answered the quiestionnaire, which contained two parts, a detailed survey about the general learning circumstances and an other one about Kolb's learning style inventory (Kolb test). Utilizing the educational achievement of these student we may point out some relations among the success in the university" and learning styles, learning strategies, environmental impacts, certain attitudes and personal characteristics. The final goal of the project is to manifest some strategic steps in order to improve the educational processes of the university, as in some cases it can be useful for supporting decisions in the near future. On the other hand it can help to accomplish better student consultancy.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0159</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Developing Engineering Expertise within Numerical Methods</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Maths in EE</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Desmond Adair</u><sup>2</sup>, Martin Jaeger<sup>1</sup> <em><sup> 1</sup>University of Tasmania, Australia, Australia,<sup> 2</sup>Nazarbayev University, Republic of Kazakhstan, Kazakhstan</em></p><p>The goal of this paper is to incorporate key findings from earlier works found in the literature, concerning the development of engineering expertise for undergraduate student; specifically here, the development of expertise within numerical methods commonly found in today's professional engineering, and, to test if the use of these findings, substantially improve student expertise. The research is based on the development of an existing course on Numerical Methods for Engineering, and the research aims are to allow student to construct deeper conceptual knowledge, to develop substantial skills to apply this conceptual knowledge, to practice their newly acquired skills and knowledge using authentic engineering projects, and finally to test if the new approach does indeed produce better engineering expertise.</p><p>It is not the intention here to spontaneously create experts from undergraduate student as expertise takes significant time to develop. People who have considerable expertise, approach problems by considering the whole problem prior to attempting specific methods and they classify problems based on deep features, such as general principles that govern the correct solution rather than shallow features, such as the relationship between objects in mechanics.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0160</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Thinking like an engineer: using engineering habits of mind to redesign engineering education for global competitiveness</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: The Attractiveness of Engineering</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Bill Lucas</u>, Janet Hanson <em>Centre for Real World Learning, University of Winchester, Winchester, UK</em></p><p>If we want to ensure that young engineers are ready to meet the challenges of the future and can operate in a global environment, we need to know how successful engineers think and act when faced with challenging problems. Once we have identified these distinctive engineering  habits of mind' (EHoM) we can then suggest how the education and training system might be re-designed to ensure the cultivation of these EHoM in school, college and university. Funded by the Royal Academy of Engineering, our research found that there was considerable agreement about the six habits of mind that engineers use most frequently when engaged in the core activities of  making' things or  making things work better'. We suggest that active teaching approach, such as PBL or CDIO, can in themselves only take the learner so far, but if the curriculum overtly articulates EHoM as an outcome of learning and provides student with opportunities to develop and practice them at all levels of the education system, more successful learning will occur. In addition to developing our earlier work at the Centre for Real World Learning in which we developed a model of practical learning, we also drew on the habits of mind approach which can be found in the engineering education community in the USA and on habits of mind developed in science and mathematics education. This presentation will outline the key findings from our interviews with engineers and engineers educators and discuss the six EHoM that were agreed through this process.</p><br style="page-break-before:always" /><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>0162</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal"><strong>Flipped learning: comparing the student experience from 1<sup>st</sup> year to postgraduate</strong></p><p class="MsoNormal">Status: 
            Accepted</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Category: Curriculum Development</p><p class="MsoNormal">
              Author's preference: Oral</p><p class="MsoNormal"><u>Keith Willey</u>, Anne Gardner, A Kadi <em>University of Technology Sydney, Sydney, NSW, Australia</em></p><p>While flipped instruction may be standard practice in many social science programs it is often promoted as a recent innovation in learning design within science and technology classrooms. Flipped instruction is a form of blended learning that replaces transmission-based lectures with more participative, interactive and collaborative learning opportunities. Activities are typically undertaken before, during and after class, freeing in class time to participate in activities often engaging with concepts at a higher level. Flipped activities typically require student to undertake out of class preparation, engage in in-class collaboration and dialogue and adopt a more independent approach to their learning.</p><p> Typically instructors focus on their student' cognitive development in relation to the subject material. However, student' expectations of how a subject is delivered and their level of meta cognitive skill development will also affect how they engage with the subject content and hence impact their learning. Our investigation is concerned with how these factors impact student' response to flipped instruction.</p><p> This paper reports the exploratory phase of a study investigating the impact of flipped instruction on first year, third year and postgraduate student. We found that most student preferred flipped instruction compared to the more traditional lecture style approach agreeing that it had a positive impact on their learning experience. There was also evidence that the different learning expectations and focus of the undergraduate student in particular those in first-year meant that many may not be ready for the responsibility and independence demanded to engage with flipped instruction without scaffolding and support.</p><p></p></body></html>